Fluorescent carbon dots driven from ayurvedic medicinal plants for cancer cell 
imaging and phototherapy.

Meena R(1), Singh R(1), Marappan G(2), Kushwaha G(3), Gupta N(4)(5), Meena R(6), 
Gupta JP(7), Agarwal RR(7), Fahmi N(1), Kushwaha OS(8).

Author information:
(1)Department of Chemistry, University of Rajasthan, Jaipur, Rajasthan, 302004, 
India.
(2)Nanoscience and Technology, Bharathiar University, Coimbatore, 641046, India.
(3)Department of Biotechnology, Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee, 247667, 
India.
(4)Trident Diagnostics Center, Trivenee, Jaipur, 302015, Rajasthan, India.
(5)Department of Radiology, Fortis Escorts Hospital, Jaipur, 302017, Rajasthan, 
India.
(6)Madan Mohan Malviya Government Ayurvedic College and Hospital, Udaipur, 
Rajasthan, 313001, India.
(7)Dr. Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan Rajasthan Ayurved University, Jodhpur, 342037, 
Rajasthan, India.
(8)Department of Chemical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Madras, 
Chennai, 600036, India.

Ayurveda based nanomaterials are recently conceptualized phenomena for 
biomedical applications especially for imaging and treatment of in vitro cancer 
cell. Wide range florescent (blue to red emission) quantum dots are versatile 
materials for imaging and sensing applications. Various procedures and 
precursors of fluorescent carbon quantum dots (CQDs) are well established and 
documented in the literature. However, expensive precursors and production, and 
time consuming process limit their economical design that need to be addressed. 
Herein, we report a cost effective simple route for fluorescent CQDs by using 
affordable ayurvedic plant's precursors such as Azadirachta Indica, 
OcimumTenuiflorum and Tridax Procumbens. Obtained quantum dots from ayurvedic 
plant leaves namely CQDs-1 (AzadirachtaIndica), CQDs-2 (OcimumTenuiflorum) and 
CQDs-3 (TridaxProcumbens) showed homogeneous size distribution (∼6-12 nm) and 
green fluorescent nature, average photo-stability, biocompatibility (more than 
85 %), cancer cell imaging and promising phototherapy for cancer and bacterial 
cell lines.
