A Review of Cytotoxic Plants of the Indian Subcontinent and a Broad-Spectrum 
Analysis of Their Bioactive Compounds.

Mazumder K(1)(2), Biswas B(1), Raja IM(1), Fukase K(3).

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacy, Jashore University of Science and Technology, Jashore 
7408, Bangladesh.
(2)School of Biomedical Sciences, Charles Sturt University, Boorooma St, Locked 
Bag 588, Wagga Wagga, New South Wales 2678, Australia.
(3)Department of Chemistry, Graduate School of Science, Osaka University, Osaka 
565-0871, Japan.

Cancer or uncontrolled cell proliferation is a major health issue worldwide and 
is the second leading cause of deaths globally. The high mortality rate and 
toxicity associated with cancer chemotherapy or radiation therapy have 
encouraged the investigation of complementary and alternative treatment methods, 
such as plant-based drugs. Moreover, over 60% of the anti-cancer drugs are 
molecules derived from plants or their synthetic derivatives. Therefore, in the 
present review, an attempt has been made to summarize the cytotoxic plants 
available in the Indian subcontinent along with a description of their 
bio-active components. The review covers 99 plants of 57 families as well as 
over 110 isolated bioactive cytotoxic compounds, amongst which at least 20 are 
new compounds. Among the reported phytoconstituents, artemisinin, lupeol, 
curcumin, and quercetin are under clinical trials, while brazilin, catechin, 
ursolic acid, β-sitosterol, and myricetin are under pharmacokinetic development. 
However, for the remaining compounds, there is little or no information 
available. Therefore, further investigations are warranted on these subcontinent 
medicinal plants as an important source of novel cytotoxic agents.
