Anti-leukemic activities of alcoholic extracts of two traditional Indian 
medicinal plants.

Bhargava S(1)(2), Malhotra H(3), Rathore OS(3), Malhotra B(2), Sharma P(2), 
Batra A(1), Sharma A(4), Chiplunkar SV(5).

Author information:
(1)a Department of Botany , University of Rajasthan , Jaipur , India.
(2)c Department of Microbiology , SMS Medical College , Jaipur , India.
(3)b Division of Medical Oncology, Department of Medicine , SMS Medical College 
, Jaipur , India.
(4)d Department of Zoology , University of Rajasthan , Jaipur , India.
(5)e Advanced Centre for Treatment, Research and Education in Cancer (ACTREC) , 
Mumbai , India.

The present work aimed to investigate the anticancer in vitro activity of two 
plants commonly used in traditional Indian medicine: Zingiber officinale Roscoe 
and Nerium oleander L. The extracts of these plants were tested in vitro on 
several human leukemic cell lines, K562, THP-1, MOLT-4 and Jurkat. Cell growth 
inhibition was observed for both plant extracts with 50% inhibitory 
concentration (IC50) values ranging between 1 and 28 μg/mL using SRB 
(sulphorodamine B) and MTT [3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl 
tetrazolium bromide] assays. Enhanced cell growth inhibition was observed when 
the extracts were combined with imatinib. Exposed cells showed cell cycle 
arrest, DNA damage and cytochrome c release, indicating that the mechanism of 
cytotoxicity could be via mitochondrial mediated apoptotic pathways. Combination 
of the extracts of these plants with standard cancer treatment may be a way of 
enhancing responses. Clinical studies in patients with chronic myeloid leukemia 
are planned at our center.