Chemopreventive potential of esculetin in 7,12-dimethylbenz(a)anthracene-induced 
hamster buccal pouch carcinogenesis.

Selvasundaram R(1), Manoharan S(2), Buddhan R(1), Neelakandan M(1), Murali Naidu 
R(3).

Author information:
(1)Department of Biochemistry and Biotechnology, Faculty of Science, Annamalai 
University, Annamalainagar, Tamil Nadu, 608002, India.
(2)Department of Biochemistry and Biotechnology, Faculty of Science, Annamalai 
University, Annamalainagar, Tamil Nadu, 608002, India. smauncd@gmail.com.
(3)Department of Oral & Maxillofacial Pathology, Rajah Muthiah Dental College & 
Hospital, Annamalai University, Annamalainagar, Tamil Nadu, India.

7,12-Dimethylbenz(a)anthracene (DMBA)-induced hamster buccal pouch 
carcinogenesis is widely preferred to assess the tumor-inhibiting efficacy of 
the medicinal plants or their constituents. The present study explores the 
tumor-inhibiting potential of esculetin by utilizing the status of lipid 
peroxidation by products (thiobarbituric acid reactive substances), antioxidants 
(vitamin E, reduced glutathione, superoxide dismutase, catalase, and glutathione 
peroxidase), and phase I and phase II detoxification agents as biochemical end 
points and by using histopathological studies as well in DMBA-induced hamster 
buccal pouch carcinogenesis. Oral tumors developed in the buccal pouch were 
subjected to histopathological studies, and were confirmed as oral squamous cell 
carcinoma. Hamsters treated with DMBA alone showed an abnormal pattern of lipid 
peroxidation, antioxidants, and detoxification agents as compared to control 
hamsters. The status of the above-mentioned biochemical markers and 
histopathological abnormalities were found to be reversed in 
DMBA + esculetin-treated hamsters. The result of the present study thus 
indicates the tumor preventive potential of esculetin in DMBA-induced oral 
carcinogenesis.
