Pharmacological properties of guggulsterones, the major active components of gum 
guggul.

Shah R(1), Gulati V, Palombo EA.

Author information:
(1)Environment and Biotechnology Centre, Faculty of Life and Social Sciences, 
Swinburne University of Technology, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, 3122, Victoria, 
Australia.

Oleo gum resin secreted by Commiphora mukul, also known as gum guggul, has been 
used widely as an ayurvedic drug. Commiphora mukul is a short thorny shrub that 
is native to the Indian subcontinent. Oleo gum resin extracted by incision of 
the bark is a very complex mixture of gum, minerals, essential oils, terpenes, 
sterols, ferrulates, flavanones and sterones. Its active constituents, the Z- 
and E-guggulsterones, have been demonstrated to exhibit their biological 
activities by binding to nuclear receptors and modulating the expression of 
proteins involved in carcinogenic activities. Guggulsterones have also been 
reported to regulate gene expression by exhibiting control over other molecular 
targets including transcription factors such as nuclear factor (NF)-κB, signal 
transducer and activator of transcription (STAT) and steroid receptors. 
Considerable scientific evidence indicates the use of gum guggul as a 
therapeutic agent in the treatment of inflammation, nervous disorders, 
hyperlipidaemia and associated cardiac disorders such as hypertension and 
ischaemia, skin disorders, cancer and urinary disorders. This review highlights 
the taxonomic details, phytochemical properties and pharmacological profile of 
gum guggul.
