Evaluation of Cytotoxicity Effects of Oleo-Gum-Resin and Its Essential Oil of 
Ferula assa-foetida and Ferulic Acid on 4T1 Breast Cancer Cells.

Bagheri SM(1)(2), Asl AA(3), Shams A(3), Mirghanizadeh-Bafghi SA(3), 
Hafizibarjin Z(1).

Author information:
(1)Department of Physiology, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, 
Yazd, Iran.
(2)Department of Neurobiomedical Research Center, Shahid Sadoughi University of 
Medical Sciences, Yazd, Iran.
(3)Department of Immunology, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, 
Yazd, Iran.

BACKGROUND: Cancer causes significant morbidity and mortality and is a major 
public health problem worldwide. Breast cancer is a leading cause of 
cancer-associated mortality in women, and the incidence is also on the rise in 
the entire world. Medicinal plants have been an important source of several 
clinically useful anticancer agents.
AIM: In this study, we studied the growth inhibitory effect of asafoetida and 
its essential oil and ferulic acid on antitumor activity using mouse breast 
cancer cell line.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: For this aim, cells were exposed to these components at 
different concentrations and for different time durations. 
3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay was 
carried out to characterize the cytotoxicity of the constituents used.
RESULTS: Our results showed that all three constituents could inhibit 4T1 cell 
proliferation. Our MTT assay results showed a significant cytotoxicity effect in 
a time- and concentration-dependent manner. It also demonstrated that essential 
oil of asafoetida has a stronger effect in decreasing viability breast cancer 
cells. Ferulic acid showed a significant effect only at a dose of 500 μg/ml.
CONCLUSIONS: Based on the results of cellular carried out in this study, we 
could demonstrate that asafoetida and its essential oil and ferulic acid have 
inhibitory effect on the growth of breast cancer cell line. As evidenced from 
these preliminary results, asafoetida and its derivative constituents may be 
considered as attractive alternatives to serve as lead compounds in drug 
development for breast cancer as an adjuvant therapy. However, much remains to 
be done before such agent could be introduced to the clinic.