Emodin suppresses Wnt signaling in human colorectal cancer cells SW480 and 
SW620.

Pooja T(1), Karunagaran D(2).

Author information:
(1)Department of Biotechnology, Bhupat and Jyoti Mehta School of Biosciences, 
Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai 600036, India. Electronic 
address: pooja256@gmail.com.
(2)Department of Biotechnology, Bhupat and Jyoti Mehta School of Biosciences, 
Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai 600036, India. Electronic 
address: karuna@iitm.ac.in.

Wnt signaling is involved in the regulation of cell proliferation, 
differentiation and apoptosis. Its aberrant activation is a key event in the 
pathogenesis and progression of human colorectal cancers. Dietary phytochemicals 
are gaining importance as chemotherapeutic agents owing to their potential to 
prevent, delay or reverse oncogenesis. Here we demonstrate that emodin 
(1,3,8-trihydroxy-6-methylanthraquinone), an anthraquinone present in the roots 
and bark of several medicinal plants, down regulates Wnt signaling pathway in 
human colorectal cancer cells (SW480 and SW620) by down regulating TCF/LEF 
transcriptional activity. Emodin significantly down regulated the expression of 
key players of Wnt signaling (β-catenin and TCF7L2) and also that of its various 
downstream targets (cyclin D1, c-Myc, snail, vimentin, MMP-2 and MMP-9). Two 
novel targets of emodin׳s action were discovered namely Wnt co-activator p300 
(down regulated) and repressor HBP1 (up regulated). Morphological changes 
induced by emodin suggest mesenchymal to epithelial transition accompanied by 
the increase in E-cadherin expression in human colorectal cancer cells but a 
differentiation marker (alkaline phosphatase) was activated only in SW620 cells 
(metastatic origin) and not in SW480 cells (primary tumor-derived). Moreover, 
our data indicate that reactive oxygen species plays a key role in 
emodin-mediated down regulation of Wnt signaling as emodin-mediated inhibition 
of migration and induction of growth arrest were partially rescued by the 
reactive oxygen species scavenger ascorbic acid. Effects of emodin shown in this 
study may provide important insights for the use of this anthraquinone as a 
potential complementary and integrated medicine for the treatment of human 
colorectal cancer.

