In Vitro Anticancer Activities of Anogeissus latifolia, Terminalia bellerica, 
Acacia catechu and Moringa oleiferna Indian Plants.

Diab KA(1), Guru SK, Bhushan S, Saxena AK.

Author information:
(1)Genetics and Cytology Department, National Research Centre, Dokki, Giza, 
Egypt E-mail : kawthar_diab@yahoo.com.

The present study was designed to evaluate in vitro anti-proliferative potential 
of extracts from four Indian medicinal plants, namely Anogeissus latifolia, 
Terminalia bellerica, Acacia catechu and Moringa oleiferna. Their cytotoxicity 
was tested in nine human cancer cell lines, including cancers of lung (A549), 
prostate (PC-3), breast (T47D and MCF-7), colon (HCT-16 and Colo-205) and 
leukemia (THP-1, HL-60 and K562) by using SRB and MTT assays. The findings 
showed that the selected plant extracts inhibited the cell proliferation of nine 
human cancer cell lines in a concentration dependent manner. The extracts 
inhibited cell viability of leukemia HL-60 and K562 cells by blocking G0/G1 
phase of the cell cycle. Interestingly, A. catechu extract at 100 μg/mL induced 
G2/M arrest in K562 cells. DNA fragmentation analysis displayed the appearance 
of a smear pattern of cell necrosis upon agarose gel electrophoresis after 
incubation of HL-60 cells with these extracts for 24 h.

