Preventive effect of berberine against DMBA-induced breast cancer in female 
Sprague Dawley rats.

Karnam KC(1), Ellutla M(1), Bodduluru LN(1), Kasala ER(2), Uppulapu SK(1), 
Kalyankumarraju M(1), Lahkar M(3).

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, National Institute of 
Pharmaceutical Education and Research (NIPER), Guwahati, Assam 781032, India.
(2)Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, National Institute of 
Pharmaceutical Education and Research (NIPER), Guwahati, Assam 781032, India. 
Electronic address: ishreddy4@gmail.com.
(3)Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, National Institute of 
Pharmaceutical Education and Research (NIPER), Guwahati, Assam 781032, India; 
Department of Pharmacology, Gauhati Medical College, Guwahati, Assam 781032, 
India.

Breast cancer is the prime cause for cancer mortality in women worldwide. The 
importance of diverse natural and dietary agents to reduce the risk of 
developing breast cancer is well established. Berberine, a natural isoquinoline 
alkaloid found in many medicinal plants is widely used in traditional Indian and 
Chinese medicine. Because of its capability to seize the cell cycle and induce 
apoptosis of numerous malignant cells, berberine has received considerable 
attention as a potential anticancer agent. In the present study, breast cancer 
was induced in Sprague Dawley (SD) rats by intragastric administration of 7, 
12-dimethylbenz[a]anthracene (DMBA) at a dose of 80mg/kg of body weight. 
Treatment of berberine (50mg/kg BW) to breast tumor bearing rats was found to be 
effective against DMBA induced mammary carcinoma. The increased levels of lipid 
peroxide (malonaldehyde), pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-1β, IL-6 and TNF-α), 
enzymatic antioxidants (SOD and CAT), non-enzymatic antioxidants (GSH and 
vitamin C) and transcription factor NF-κB were decreased significantly by 
administration of berberine. Furthermore, RT-PCR and western blot analysis 
showed the down-regulation of NF-κB and PCNA in breast tumors. Histopathological 
studies validated that berberine is effective against DMBA induced ductal 
carcinoma & invasive carcinoma. Altogether, these findings demonstrate the 
preventive role of berberine against DMBA induced mammary carcinoma in SD rats.

