Plant phenyl-propanoids-conjugated silver nanoparticles from edible plant Suaeda 
maritima (L.) dumort. Inhibit proliferation of K562-human myeloid leukemia 
cells.

Rajendran N(1), Subramaniam S(2), Raja MRC(2), Brindha P(1), Kar Mahapatra S(2), 
Sivasubramanian A(2).

Author information:
(1)a CARISM, SASTRA University , Thanjavur , India.
(2)b School of Chemical and Biotechnology, SASTRA University , Thanjavur , 
India.

The present study portrays the isolation of four phenylpropanoids - ferulic acid 
(FA), sinapic acid (SA), caffeic acid (CA), and chlorogenic acid (CHA) from the 
water extract of Suaeda maritima (L.) Dumort, a phytochemically less explored 
Indian medicinal plant. Further, synthesis and characterization of silver and 
gold nanoparticles using the isolated phenylpropanoids were done. The silver 
nanoparticles synthesized from S. maritima water extract along with silver 
nano-conjugated forms of the isolated compounds exhibited appreciable 
anti-leukemic activity against K562 cells (human myeloid leukemia). Especially, 
the ferulic and CA-conjugated silver nanoparticles showed significant (P < .01) 
activity against leukemia.
