Molecular docking, QSAR and ADMET studies of withanolide analogs against breast 
cancer.

Yadav DK(1), Kumar S(2), Saloni(1), Singh H(3), Kim MH(1), Sharma P(4), Misra 
S(4), Khan F(5).

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, Gachon University, Yeonsu-gu, 
Incheon, Republic of Korea.
(2)Faculty of Pharmacy, Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, Babu Banarasi 
Das Northern India Institute of Technology, Lucknow.
(3)Department of Bioinformatics, Indian Council of Medical Research, New Delhi.
(4)Department of Biochemistry, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur.
(5)Metabolic & Structural Biology Department, CSIR-Central Institute of 
Medicinal & Aromatic Plant, Lucknow, India.

Withanolides are a group of pharmacologically active compounds present in most 
prodigal amounts in roots and leaves of Withania somnifera (Indian ginseng), one 
of the most important medicinal plants of Indian traditional practice of 
medicine. Withanolides are steroidal lactones (highly oxygenated C-28 
phytochemicals) and have been reported to exhibit immunomodulatory, anticancer 
and other activities. In the present study, a quantitative structure activity 
relationship (QSAR) model was developed by a forward stepwise multiple linear 
regression method to predict the activity of withanolide analogs against human 
breast cancer. The most effective QSAR model for anticancer activity against the 
SK-Br-3 cell showed the best correlation with activity (r2=0.93 and rCV2 =0.90). 
Similarly, cross-validation regression coefficient (rCV2=0.85) of the best QSAR 
model against the MCF7/BUS cells showed a high correlation (r2=0.91). In 
particular, compounds CID_73621, CID_435144, CID_301751 and CID_3372729 have a 
marked antiproliferative activity against the MCF7/BUS cells, while 
2,3-dihydrowithaferin A-3-beta-O-sulfate, withanolide 5, withanolide A, 
withaferin A, CID_10413139, CID_11294368, CID_53477765, CID_135887, CID_301751 
and CID_3372729 have a high activity against the Sk-Br-3 cells compared to 
standard drugs 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) and camptothecin. Molecular docking was 
performed to study the binding conformations and different bonding behaviors, in 
order to reveal the plausible mechanism of action behind higher accumulation of 
active withanolide analogs with β-tubulin. The results of the present study may 
help in the designing of lead compound with improved activity.
