Antiplasmodial, anti-inflammatory and cytotoxic activities of various plant 
extracts from the Mascarene Archipelago.

Jonville MC(1), Kodja H, Strasberg D, Pichette A, Ollivier E, Frédérich M, 
Angenot L, Legault J.

Author information:
(1)Université de Liège, CIRM, Laboratoire de Pharmacognosie (B36), Avenue de 
l'Hôpital 1, Liège, Belgium. MC.Jonville@ulg.ac.be

AIM OF THE STUDY: Antiplasmodial activity, inhibition of nitric oxide (NO) 
overproduction, and anti-proliferative activity were investigated in vitro to 
evaluate the bioactive potential of the traditional pharmacopoeia of the 
Mascarene Archipelago, which is known for its biodiversity and for the richness 
of its endemic flora.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: A total of 45 methanol (MeOH) and dichloromethane (DCM) 
extracts were prepared from 19 plant species collected on Réunion and Mauritius 
Islands. Ninety-six-well microplate assays were performed on chloroquine 
sensitive Plasmodium falciparum 3D7 strain, on LPS-stimulated Raw 264.7 murine 
macrophages and on A-549, DLD-1 and WS1 human cells. Activity was evaluated 
through spectrophotometric methods.
RESULTS: Activity was attributed to plant extracts expressing IC(50)<50μg/ml for 
antiplasmodial response, IC(50)<100μg/ml for cytotoxicity, and IC(50)<130μg/ml 
for anti-inflammatory reaction. The majority of the extracts tested (69%) 
exhibited potency in at least one of these three types of activity. This is the 
first report describing promising antiplasmodial activity (IC(50)<15μg/ml) for 
Psiadia dentata DCM extract and Terminalia bentzoe MeOH bark extract. NO 
inhibition assay revealed seven interesting plants, described for the first time 
as anti-inflammatory: Aphloia theiformis, Buddleja salviifolia, Eupatorium 
riparium, Hiptage benghalensis, Psiadia arguta, Psiadia dentata, and Scutia 
commersonii. Finally, anti-proliferative activity was observed for two endemic 
species, Geniostoma borbonicum and Nuxia verticillata.
CONCLUSION: Using the criterion of endemism as part of the criteria for 
traditional medicinal use raises the chances of finding original active 
principles. In our case, 86% of the endemic plants tested displayed 
pharmacological interest.

