Evaluating the Anticancer Potential of Ethanolic Gall Extract of Terminalia 
chebula (Gaertn.) Retz. (Combretaceae).

Ravi Shankara BE(1), Ramachandra YL(2), Rajan SS(2), Ganapathy PS(3), Yarla 
NS(4), Richard SA(5), Dhananjaya BL(6).

Author information:
(1)Department of Chemistry, School of Graduate Studies, Jain University, 
Chamrajpet, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India; Research Unit in Vrukshayurveda, A 
Division of Centre for Advanced Studies in Biosciences, Jain University, 
Chamrajpet, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India; Department of PG Studies and Research 
in Biotechnology, Kuvempu University, Shankaraghatta, Mysore, Karnataka, India.
(2)Department of PG Studies and Research in Biotechnology, Kuvempu University, 
Shankaraghatta, Mysore, Karnataka, India.
(3)Research Unit in Vrukshayurveda, A Division of Centre for Advanced Studies in 
Biosciences, Jain University, Chamrajpet, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India.
(4)Department of Biochemistry, Institute of Science, GITAM University, 
Visakhapatnam, Andhra Pradesh, India.
(5)Department of Biochemistry, University of Mysore, Mysore, Karnataka, India.
(6)Toxinology/Toxicology and Drug Discovery Unit, Centre for Emerging 
Technologies, Jain University, Ramanagara, Karnataka, India.

Plants have been an important source for discovery of anticancer compounds. With 
the current decline in the number of new molecular entities from the 
pharmaceutical industry, novel anticancer agents are being sought from 
traditional medicines; therefore the anticancer efficacy of many plants that are 
used in traditional medicine is yet to be verified. The objective of the study 
was to evaluate the cytotoxic potential of ethanolic leaf gall extract of 
Terminalia chebula are evaluated against buffalo rat liver 3A, MCF-7 (Human 
mammary gland adenocarcinoma) and A-549 (Human lung cancer) cell lines. The 
cytotoxic effect of the ethanolic extract was evaluated by MTT assay. The 
extract was potent and effective in inducing cytotoxic effects in all the cell 
lines with an IC50 value of 305.18 ± 1.7 μg/mL, 643.13 ± 4.2 μg/mL, and 208.16 ± 
3.7 μ/mL, respectively. The extract was more effective against A549 cell lines 
when compared to others. The presences of phenolics, triterpenoids, and 
flavonoids were identified in the extract. The extract showed total phenolic and 
flavonoid content of 478 ± 2.2 mg of gallic acid equivalent/g d.w and 538 ± 1.4 
mg of quercetinequivalent/g d.w, respectively. This higher content of total 
phenolics and flavonoids found in the ethanolic extract was directly associated 
to higher cytotoxicity activity.
CONCLUSION: The ethanolic leaf gall extract of T. chebula showed effective 
cytotoxic activities; which might be attributed to the phenolics/flavonoids 
present in higher concentration. Future work will be interesting to know the 
chemical composition of the extract and also better understand the mechanism of 
action of the constituents present in the extract to develop it as drug for 
therapeutic application.
SUMMARY: The present investigation establishes the anticancer activities of T. 
chebula leaf gall extracts on BRL3A, MCF-7, and A-549 cells. Presumably, these 
activities could be attributed in part to the phenolics/flavanoids features of 
the extract that has been demonstrated to act as cytotoxic agents. The 
experimental evidence obtained in the laboratory model could provide a rationale 
for the traditional use of plant as a source of easily available effective 
anticancer agents to the people, particularly in developing countries.

