Par-4 dependent modulation of cellular β-catenin by medicinal plant natural 
product derivative 3-azido Withaferin A.

Amin H(1)(2), Nayak D(1), Ur Rasool R(1), Chakraborty S(1), Kumar A(3), Yousuf 
K(4), Sharma PR(1), Ahmed Z(1), Sharma N(1), Magotra A(1), Mukherjee D(4), Kumar 
LD(3), Goswami A(1).

Author information:
(1)Cancer Pharmacology Division, Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine 
(CSIR), Canal Road, Jammu Tawi, Jammu and Kashmir, India.
(2)School of Biosciences and Biotechnology, Baba Ghulam Shah Badshah University, 
Rajouri, Jammu and Kashmir, India.
(3)Center for Cellular and Molecular Biology, Uppal Road, Hyderabad, Andra 
Pradesh, India.
(4)Natural Product Chemistry, Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine (CSIR), 
Canal Road, Jammu Tawi, Jammu and Kashmir, India.

Here, we provide evidences that natural product derivative 3-azido Withaferin A 
(3-AWA) abrogated EMT and invasion by modulating β-catenin localization and its 
transcriptional activity in the prostate as well as in breast cancer cells. This 
study, for the first time, reveals 3-AWA treatment consistently sequestered 
nuclear β-catenin and augmented its cytoplasmic pool as evidenced by reducing 
β-catenin transcriptional activity in these cells. Moreover, 3-AWA treatment 
triggered robust induction of pro-apoptotic intracellular Par-4, attenuated Akt 
activity and rescued Phospho-GSK3β (by Akt) to promote β-catenin 
destabilization. Further, our in vitro studies demonstrate that 3-AWA treatment 
amplified E-cadherin expression along with sharp downregulation of c-Myc and 
cyclin D1 proteins. Strikingly, endogenous Par-4 knock down by siRNA underscored 
3-AWA mediated inhibition of nuclear β-catenin was Par-4 dependent and 
suppression of Par-4 activity, either by Bcl-2 or by Ras transfection, restored 
the nuclear β-catenin level suggesting Par-4 mediated β-catenin regulation was 
not promiscuous. In vivo results further demonstrated that 3-AWA was effective 
inhibitor of tumor growth and immunohistochemical studies indicated that 
increased expression of total β-catenin and decreased expression of 
phospho-β-catenin and Par-4 in breast cancer tissues as compared to normal 
breast tissue suggesting Par-4 and β-catenin proteins are mutually regulated and 
inversely co-related in normal as well as cancer condition. Thus, strategic 
regulation of intracellular Par-4 by 3-AWA in diverse cancers could be an 
effective tool to control cancer cell metastasis. Conclusively, this report puts 
forward a novel approach of controlling deregulated β-catenin signaling by 3-AWA 
induced Par-4 protein.

