Invitro Anti-mycotic Activity of Hydro Alcoholic Extracts of Some Indian 
Medicinal Plants against Fluconazole Resistant Candida albicans.

Varadarajan S(1), Narasimhan M(2), Malaisamy M(3), Duraipandian C(4).

Author information:
(1)Senior Research Fellow, Department of Oral Pathology, Faculty of Dental 
sciences, Sri Ramachandra University , Chennai, India .
(2)Professor and Head, Department of Oral Pathology, Faculty of Dental Sciences, 
Sri Ramachandra University , Chennai, India .
(3)Research Scholar, Center for Advanced Studies in Botany, Guindy Campus, 
University of Madras , Chennai, India .
(4)Principal, College of Pharmacy, Sri Ramachandra University .

BACKGROUND: Candidiasis is one of the most common opportunistic infections 
caused by Candida albicans. Fluconazole is the drug of choice for prevention and 
management of this condition. However, the emergence of fluconazole resistant 
candidal strains has become a major concern. Many herbs like fenugreek, 
cinnamon, papaya, oregano, garlic are rich in phytochemical constituents known 
to express antimycotic activity. With the available information, the present 
research study was carried out to assess the invitro anti-mycotic activity of 
hydro alcoholic extracts of Trigonella foenum-graecum seeds, Cinnamomum verum 
bark and Carica papaya leaves and seeds against fluconazole resistant Candida 
albicans.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Hydro alcoholic extracts of Trigonella foenum-graecum 
(seeds), Cinnamomum verum (bark), Carica papaya CO.2 strain (male and female 
leaves) and Carica papaya CO.2 strain (seeds) were prepared by maceration. The 
anti-mycotic activity of the prepared extracts against Candida albicans was 
assessed by agar well diffusion method. Three independent experiments were 
performed in triplicates and the mean and standard deviation were calculated. 
Minimum inhibitory concentration was determined.
RESULTS: The results of the present study revealed that all the extracts 
exhibited anti-mycotic activity in a dose dependent manner and minimum 
inhibitory concentration of all the extracts was found to be 15.62 μg/ml.
CONCLUSION: The results of the present study shed light on the fact that plant 
extracts could be used not only as an alternate drug for management of 
fluconazole resistant candidiasis but also explored further for oral cancer 
prevention as a therapeutic adjunct.