Synthesis of novel anticancer iridoid derivatives and their cell cycle arrest 
and caspase dependent apoptosis.

Pandeti S(1), Sharma K(2), Bathula SR(3), Tadigoppula N(4).

Author information:
(1)Medicinal and Process Chemistry Division, CSIR-Central Drug Research 
Institute, Lucknow 226 001, UP, India.
(2)Pharmaceutics Division, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow 226 
001, UP, India.
(3)Pharmaceutics Division, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow 226 
001, UP, India. Electronic address: bsreddy@cdri.res.in.
(4)Medicinal and Process Chemistry Division, CSIR-Central Drug Research 
Institute, Lucknow 226 001, UP, India. Electronic address: 
t_narendra@cdri.res.in.

Nyctanthes arbortristis Linn (Oleaceae) is widely distributed in sub-Himalayan 
regions and southwards to Godavari, India commonly known as Harsingar and Night 
Jasmine. In continuation of our drug discovery programme on Indian medicinal 
plants, we isolated arbortristoside-A (1) and 7-O-trans-cinnamoyl 
6β-hydroxyloganin (2) from the seeds of N. Arbortristis, which exhibited 
moderate in vitro anticancer activity. Chemical transformation of 2 led to 
significant improvement in the activity in derivative 8 and 15 against HepG2 
(human hepatocellular carcinoma), MCF-7 (breast adenocarcinoma) cell lines. The 
compounds 8 and 15 were also capable of cell cycle arrest and caspase dependent 
apoptosis in HepG2 cell lines. These iridoid derivatives hold promise for 
developing safer alternatives to the marketed drugs.
