Production of bioactive cyclotides in somatic embryos of Viola odorata.

Narayani M(1), Sai Varsha MKN(1), Potunuru UR(1), Sofi Beaula W(1), Rayala 
SK(1), Dixit M(1), Chadha A(1), Srivastava S(2).

Author information:
(1)Department of Biotechnology, Bhupat & Jyoti Mehta School of Biosciences, 
Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai-600 036, India.
(2)Department of Biotechnology, Bhupat & Jyoti Mehta School of Biosciences, 
Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai-600 036, India. Electronic 
address: smita@iitm.ac.in.

Viola odorata L. (Violaceae), an Indian medicinal plant, contains a plethora of 
cyclotides, which are a class of cyclic peptides derived from plants, possessing 
several applications. Somatic embryo culture of V. odorata was developed, via 
indirect somatic embryogenesis, to serve as an alternative to natural plant 
biomass for sustainable and continuous production of its bioactive ingredients, 
such as cyclotides. Among the various combinations of phytohormones tested, 
Murashige and Skoog medium supplemented with 1 mg/l thidiazuron gave rise to the 
maximum frequency of induction (86.7%) and a high number of somatic embryos (3) 
from an embryogenic callus. Identification and characterization of cyclotides in 
the somatic embryos were carried out using a Fourier transform mass spectrometer 
coupled with liquid chromatography (LC-FTMS). Among the cyclotides identified in 
the study, few were found to be exclusively present in the somatic embryo 
culture. Furthermore, the relative abundance of the cyclotides was higher in 
somatic embryo extract than in the natural plant extract. The biological 
activities (cytotoxic, haemolytic and antimicrobial) of the somatic embryos and 
the parent plant were compared. Unlike the natural plants, the somatic embryo 
extracts demonstrated specificity i.e. they were found to be potent against 
cancerous cells but not against non-cancerous cell line or red blood cells. In 
contrast to the plant extract, the somatic embryos extracts were found to be 
potent against Escherichia coli and Staphylococcus aureus. These results suggest 
that somatic embryos of V. odorata (rich in cyclotides) can be used as an 
alternative to plant biomass for its therapeutic applications and germplasm 
conservation.
