Effect of Methanolic Extract of Dandelion Roots on Cancer Cell Lines and 
AMP-Activated Protein Kinase Pathway.

Rehman G(1), Hamayun M(2), Iqbal A(3), Khan SA(4), Khan H(5), Shehzad A(6), Khan 
AL(7), Hussain A(2), Kim HY(8), Ahmad J(4), Ahmad A(9), Ali A(1), Lee 
IJ(10)(11).

Author information:
(1)Department of Zoology, Abdul Wali Khan University Mardan, Mardan, Pakistan.
(2)Department of Botany, Abdul Wali Khan University Mardan, Mardan, Pakistan.
(3)Department of Agriculture, Abdul Wali Khan University Mardan, Mardan, 
Pakistan.
(4)Centre of Biotechnology and Microbiology, University of Peshawar, Peshawar, 
Pakistan.
(5)Department of Agronomy, University of Agriculture Peshawar, Peshawar, 
Pakistan.
(6)Department of Biomedical Engineering and Sciences, SMME, National University 
of Sciences and Technology (NUST), Islamabad, Pakistan.
(7)UoN Chair of Oman's Medicinal Plants and Marine Natural Products University 
of Nizwa, Nizwa, Oman.
(8)Korea Institute of Science and Technology, Gangneung, South Korea.
(9)Department of Biotechnology, Abdul Wali Khan University Mardan, Mardan, 
Pakistan.
(10)School of Applied Biosciences, Kyungpook National University, Daegu, South 
Korea.
(11)Research Institute for Dok-do and Ulleung-do Island, Kyungpook National 
University, Daegu, South Korea.

Ethnomedicinal knowledge of plant-derived bioactives could help us in 
discovering new therapeutic compounds of great potential. Certainly, dandelion 
has been used in traditional ethno-medicinal systems (i.e., Chinese, Arabian, 
Indian, and Native American) to treat different types of cancer. Though, 
dandelion is highly vigorous, but the potential mode of action is still unclear. 
In the current study, the antiproliferative activity of methanolic extracts of 
dandelion root (MEDr) on cell viability of HepG2, MCF7, HCT116, and normal Hs27 
was investigated. It was observed that MEDr (500 μg/mL) drastically decreased 
the growth of HepG2 cell line, while the effect on MCF7 and HCT116 cell lines 
was less pronounced and no effect has been observed in Hs27 cell lines. The MEDr 
also enhanced the phosphorylation level of AMPK of HepG2 cells, which considered 
crucial in cancer treatment and other metabolic diseases. The AMPK activation by 
MEDr noticed in the current study has never been reported previously. The 
results regarding the number of apoptotic cells (HepG2 cells) were in line with 
the cell viability test. The current observations clearly demonstrated the 
potency of MEDr against liver cancer with validation that dandelion could 
control AMPK and thus cancer in the treated cell lines.
