Antiproliferative efficacy of curcumin mimics through microtubule 
destabilization.

Khwaja S(1), Fatima K(1), Hasanain M(2), Behera C(3), Kour A(3), Singh A(1), 
Luqman S(1), Sarkar J(2), Chanda D(1), Shanker K(1), Gupta AK(1), Mondhe DM(4), 
Negi AS(5).

Author information:
(1)CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants (CSIR-CIMAP), Kukrail 
Picnic Spot Road, P.O. CIMAP, Lucknow, 226015, India.
(2)CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute (CSIR-CDRI), B.S. 10/1, Sector-10, 
Janakipuram Extension, Sitapur Road, Lucknow, 226031, India.
(3)CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine (CSIR-IIIM), Canal Road, Jammu, 
180001, India.
(4)CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine (CSIR-IIIM), Canal Road, Jammu, 
180001, India. Electronic address: dmmondhe@iiim.ac.in.
(5)CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants (CSIR-CIMAP), Kukrail 
Picnic Spot Road, P.O. CIMAP, Lucknow, 226015, India. Electronic address: 
as.negi@cimap.res.in.

Curcumin possesses an attractive chemical structure with highly conjugated 
diferuloylmethane core. Curcumin mimics have been designed and prepared with an 
additional bridged phenyl ring in conjugation. Fourteen diverse analogues were 
evaluated against a panel of human cancer cell lines. The best analogue of the 
series i.e. compound 6a exhibited potent cytotoxicity against A431, epidermoid 
carcinoma cell line (IC50 = 1.5 μM) and DLD1, colorectal adenocarcinoma cell 
line (IC50 = 6.9 μM). In tubulin kinetics experiment, compound 6a destabilized 
polymerisation process (IC50 = 4.68 μM). In cell cycle analysis, compound 6a 
exerted G2/M phase arrest in A431 cells and induced apoptosis. In Ehrlich 
Ascites Carcinoma in Swiss-albino mice, compound 6a showed 78.6% tumour 
reduction at 80 mg/kg dose and 57% solid tumour reduction at 150 mg/kg dose. 
Further, in acute-oral toxicity experiment in rodent model, compound 6a was 
given in three different oral doses to Swiss albino mice. There were 
non-significant changes in various biochemical parameters and major body organs 
studied, including their absolute and relative weights. It was tolerable up to 
300 mg/kg dose in Swiss-albino mice. The present study shows that the novel 
curcumin mimic 6a is a safe and efficacious anticancer compound. However, it 
needs to be optimized for better efficacy.

