Regiospecific Synthesis of Ring A Fused Withaferin A Isoxazoline Analogues: 
Induction of Premature Senescence by W-2b in Proliferating Cancer Cells.

Rasool F(1)(2), Nayak D(1)(3), Katoch A(1)(3), Faheem MM(1)(3), Yousuf SK(1)(4), 
Hussain N(1)(2), Belawal C(5), Satti NK(5), Goswami A(6)(7), Mukherjee D(8)(9).

Author information:
(1)Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), New Delhi, India.
(2)Natural Product Chemistry-Microbes, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative 
Medicine, Jammu, 180001, India.
(3)Cancer Pharmacology Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine, 
Jammu, 180001, India.
(4)Medicinal Chemistry Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine, 
Srinagar, 190005, India.
(5)Natural Product Chemistry-Plants, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative 
Medicine, Jammu, 180001, India.
(6)Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), New Delhi, India. 
agoswami@iiim.ac.in.
(7)Cancer Pharmacology Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine, 
Jammu, 180001, India. agoswami@iiim.ac.in.
(8)Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), New Delhi, India. 
dmukherjee@iiim.ac.in.
(9)Natural Product Chemistry-Microbes, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative 
Medicine, Jammu, 180001, India. dmukherjee@iiim.ac.in.

Induction of premature senescence represents a novel functional strategy to curb 
the uncontrolled proliferation of malignant cancer cells. This study unveils the 
regiospecific synthesis of novel isoxazoline derivatives condensed to ring A of 
medicinal plant product Withaferin-A. Intriguingly, the cis fused products with 
β-oriented hydrogen exhibited excellent cytotoxic activities against 
proliferating human breast cancer MCF7 and colorectal cancer HCT-116 cells. The 
most potent derivative W-2b triggered premature senescence along with increase 
in senescence-associated β-galactosidase activity, G2/M cell cycle arrest, and 
induction of senescence-specific marker p21Waf1/Cip1 at its sub-toxic 
concentration. W-2b conferred a robust increase in phosphorylation of mammalian 
checkpoint kinase-2 (Chk2) in cancer cells in a dose-dependent manner. Silencing 
of endogenous Chk2 by siRNA divulged that the amplification of p21 expression 
and senescence by W-2b was Chk2-dependent. Chk2 activation (either by ectopic 
overexpression or through treatment with W-2b) suppressed NM23-H1 signaling axis 
involved in cancer cell proliferation. Finally, W-2b showed excellent in vivo 
efficacy with 83.8% inhibition of tumor growth at a dose of 25 mg/kg, b.w. in 
mouse mammary carcinoma model. Our study claims that W-2b could be a potential 
candidate to limit aberrant cellular proliferation rendering promising 
improvement in the treatment regime in cancer patients.
