Phytochemicals of Salacia oblonga responsible for free radical scavenging and 
antiproliferative activity against breast cancer cell lines (MDA-MB-231).

Musini A(1), Rao JP(1), Giri A(1).

Author information:
(1)Centre for Biotechnology, Institute of Science and Technology, Jawaharlal 
Nehru Technological University Hyderabad, Hyderabad, India.

Salacia oblonga, an inhabitant of tropical regions has been used in traditional 
Indian medicinal systems. Phytochemicals were extracted in methanol from the 
plant and analyzed for various biological activities. The results of biochemical 
tests for total phenolics (297 ± 0.005 and 275 ± 0.006) and flavonoids 
(95 ± 0.004 and 61.6 ± 0.004) in the aerial and root parts were indicated as 
Gallic acid and quercetin equivalents respectively. The Aerial and root extracts 
showed strong reducing ability based on reducing power and FRAP assays. The 
extracts exhibited significant IC50 values in DPPH, super oxide and nitric oxide 
radical scavenging assays. The extracts displayed low IC50 values (<50 μg/ml) 
when assessed for antiproliferative activity against breast cancer cell lines 
using the MTT assay. GC-MS analysis of methanolic extracts have revealed the 
presence of compounds viz. n-Hexadecanoic acid, N-Methoxy-N-methylacetamide, 
Ursa-9(11), 12-dien-3-ol, Gamma-sitosterol etc., that might be potential 
candidates for the biological activity exhibited by the extract.
