Phytochemical profile and pharmacological activity of Aegle marmelos Linn.

Manandhar B(1), Paudel KR(1), Sharma B(2), Karki R(3).

Author information:
(1)Department of Oriental Medicine Resources, Mokpo National University, 
Muan-gun, Jeonnam 534-729, South Korea.
(2)School of Medicine and Public Health, The University of Newcastle, Newcastle 
2305, New South Wales, Australia.
(3)Department of Oriental Medicine Resources, Mokpo National University, 
Muan-gun, Jeonnam 534-729, South Korea. Electronic address: 
rajmankarki@gmail.com.

Aegle marmelos Linn. (Rutaceae), commonly known as "bael" in Nepal and India, is 
a valuable medicinal plant and is considered sacred by the Hindus. It is used to 
cure several diseases in the Indian traditional medicine system of Ayurveda and 
has had similar uses among many ethnic communities residing in Indian 
subcontinent for over 5000 years. Its leaves, bark, stem, fruits and seeds have 
been used for various medicinal purposes. Bael fruits are especially effective 
in the treatment of chronic diarrhea, dysentery and peptic ulcers, while they 
are also useful as a laxative and cure for respiratory infections. Scientific 
studies have validated many of the ethnomedicinal uses of A. marmelos, which 
include antibacterial, antiviral, antidiarrheal, gastroprotective, 
anti-ulcerative colitis, hepatoprotective, antidiabetic, cardioprotective and 
radioprotective effects. Recently, this plant has also received attention as an 
anticancer agent for the treatment of various types of cancers. Thus, this 
review focuses on scientific evidence verifying the important pharmacological 
activity such as antioxidant, antidiabetic, antimicrobial, hepatoprotective, 
cardioprotective and anticancer activity of A. marmelos.