Synthesis and biological evaluation of glucosyl curcuminoids.

Bhaskar Rao A(1), Prasad E, Deepthi SS, Ansari IA.

Author information:
(1)Medicinal Chemistry and Pharmacology Division, CSIR - Indian Institute of 
Chemical Technology, Tarnaka, Hyderabad, India.

Medicinal plants proved to be a rich source in exploring a variety of lead 
structures in the development of new drugs. The natural curcuminoids have gained 
considerable attention in recent years for their multiple beneficial 
pharmacological and biological activities. Clinical application of these 
curcuminoids is often impaired due to their poor water solubility, resulting in 
low in vivo bioavailability of the active compound in humans. The objective of 
the present study is to synthesize glucosyl conjugates of curcumin 1 and 
tetrahydrocurcumin 4 and to evaluate their biological activities. The study 
highlights the synthesis of curcumin-β-di-glucoside 3 (yield 71%) and 
tetrahydrocurcumin-β-di-glucoside 6 (yield 64%) in good yields in a biphasic 
reaction medium using a phase transfer catalyst under simple and ecofriendly 
conditions. Both the glucosyl curcuminoids showed enhanced antioxidant, 
tyrosinase enzyme inhibitory, antimicrobial and potent cytotoxic activity. The 
improved biological activity may be due to the increased solubility of the 
glucosyl conjugated compounds compared to the native curcuminoids; this was 
further confirmed by partition coefficient studies. Thus, the synthesized 
glucosyl curcumin may serve as promising future therapeutic molecule in the 
management of cancer, whereas glucosyl tetrahydrocurcumin can be a useful 
ingredient in achromatic food and in cosmetic applications.

