Synthesis of a series of novel dihydroartemisinin monomers and dimers containing 
chalcone as a linker and their anticancer activity.

Gaur R(1), Pathania AS(2), Malik FA(3), Bhakuni RS(4), Verma RK(5).

Author information:
(1)Medicinal Chemistry Department, Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic 
Plants, Lucknow, 226015, India; Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research 
(AcSIR), New Delhi, 110001, India.
(2)Department of Cancer Pharmacology, Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine, 
Canal Road Jammu, Jammu and Kashmir, 180001, India; Academy of Scientific and 
Innovative Research (AcSIR), New Delhi, 110001, India.
(3)Department of Cancer Pharmacology, Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine, 
Canal Road Jammu, Jammu and Kashmir, 180001, India; Academy of Scientific and 
Innovative Research (AcSIR), New Delhi, 110001, India. Electronic address: 
fmalik@iiim.ac.in.
(4)Medicinal Chemistry Department, Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic 
Plants, Lucknow, 226015, India; Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research 
(AcSIR), New Delhi, 110001, India. Electronic address: bhakunirs2000@gmail.com.
(5)Medicinal Chemistry Department, Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic 
Plants, Lucknow, 226015, India.

A new series of monomer and dimer derivatives of dihydroartemisinin (DHA) 
containing substituted chalcones as a linker were synthesized and investigated 
for their cytotoxicity in human cancer cell lines HL-60 (leukemia), Mia PaCa-2 
(pancreatic cancer), PC-3 (prostate cancer), LS180 (colon cancer) and HEPG2 
(hepatocellular carcinoma). Some of these derivatives have greater 
antiproliferative and cytotoxic effects in tested cell lines than parent 
compound DHA. The structures of the all compounds were confirmed by IR, (1)H NMR 
and mass spectral data. Among the new derivatives, compounds 8, 14, 15, 20 and 
24 were found to be more active than parent DHA against tested human cancer cell 
lines. DHA derivatives were found to be most active in human leukemia cell lines 
with compounds 8, 14, 15, 20 and 24 showed IC50 values less than 1 μM for 48 h 
whereas DHA has IC50 value of 2 μM at same time period. The most potent 
compounds 8 with IC50 = 0.3 μM (at par with doxorubicin (IC50 = 0.3 μM)) and 15 
with IC50 = 0.4 μM, of the series, six and three times active than DHA (with 
IC50 = 2 μM) respectively were selected for further mechanistic work in human 
leukemia HL-60 cells.

