Cytotoxicity of medicinal plants of the West-Canadian Gwich׳in Native Americans 
towards sensitive and multidrug-resistant cancer cells.

Karadeniz A(1), Alexie G(2), Greten HJ(3), Andersch K(4), Efferth T(5).

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmaceutical Biology, Institute of Pharmacy and Biochemistry, 
Johannes Gutenberg University, Mainz, Germany; Mehmet Akif Ersoy University, 
Biology Department, Burdur, Turkey.
(2)Fort McPerson, Northwest Territories, Canada.
(3)Abel Salazar Biomedical Sciences Institute, University of Porto, Portugal; 
Heidelberg School of Chinese Medicine, Heidelberg, Germany.
(4)Wilderness International, Dresden, Germany; Wilderness International, Stony 
Plain, Alberta, Canada.
(5)Department of Pharmaceutical Biology, Institute of Pharmacy and Biochemistry, 
Johannes Gutenberg University, Mainz, Germany. Electronic address: 
efferth@uni-mainz.de.

ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: Traditional medicine of the Native Americans has 
a long tradition of medicinal plants, which also influenced modern oncology. For 
instance, podophyllotoxin the active ingredient of Podophyllum peltatum L. 
(Berberidaceae) used by Native Americans to treat warts led to the development 
of etoposide and teniposide. In the present investigation, we studied 10 
medicinal plants used by the Gwich׳in First Nation of West-Canada, which have 
been used against diverse diseases including cancer.
MATERIAL AND METHODS: Sensitive and multidrug-resistant (MDR) tumor cell lines 
expressing various ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporters 
(P-glycoprotein/ABCB1/MDR1, MRP1/ABCC1, or BCRP/ABCG2) have been used. 
Cytotoxicity was determined by the resazurin assay.
RESULTS: Arctium minus Bernh. (Asteraceae). Lysichiton americanus Hultén & St. 
John (Araceae), and Maianthemum dilatatum (Alph.Wood) A.Nelson & 
J.F.Macbr.(Asparagaceae) were cytotoxic with IC50 values ranging from 2.40 to 
86.35 µg/mL. The MDR cell lines did not exert cross-resistance to these 
extracts.
CONCLUSION: As these medicinal plants of the West-Canadian Gwich׳in First Nation 
were not involved in classical drug resistance mechanisms and might therefore be 
valuable to bypass anticancer drug resistance in refractory tumors.