Bioactivity-guided isolation of cytotoxic constituents from three medicinal 
plants.

Hullatti K(1), Pathade N, Mandavkar Y, Godavarthi A, Biradi M.

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacognosy and Phytochemistry, KLE University's College of 
Pharmacy, Belgaum, Karnataka, India. drhullatti@klepharm.edu

CONTEXT: The ethanol extracts and their fractions of three Indian medicinal 
plants, Ervatamia coronaria (Jacq.) Stapf, (Apocynaceae), Mimosa pudica L. 
(Mimosaceae) and Caesalpinia bonduc (L.) Roxb. (Caesalpiniaceae) were tested for 
their cytotoxic activity in the brine shrimp lethality (BSL) bioassay and in 
various cancer cell lines. The plants were selected based on their traditional 
use in the treatment of cancer/tumors.
OBJECTIVES: To investigate the in vitro cytotoxicity of Ervatamia coronaria, 
Mimosa pudica and Caesalpinia bonduc.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Ethanolic extracts and their fractions of E. coronaria, 
M. pudica and C. bonduc were subjected to cytotoxicity studies using BSL 
bioassay method with concentrations of 10, 50, 100, 500 and 1000 µg/ml. The 
alkaloid fraction of E. coronaria with significant cytotoxicity in BSL bioassay 
was subjected to in vitro cytotoxicity studies with HT-29, A-549, HepG-2, MCF-7 
and L-6 cell lines at concentrations of 12.5, 25, 50, 100 and 200 µg/ml and a 
DNA fragmentation study using the HT-29 cell line.
RESULTS: The alkaloid fractions of E. coronaria and M. pudica showed significant 
cytotoxicity with LC50 values of 65.83 and 85.10 µg/ml in the BSL bioassay, 
respectively. The purified alkaloid fraction of E. coronaria exhibited highest 
cytotoxicity in HT-29, A-549 and MCF-7 cell lines with IC50 values of 32.5, 47.5 
and 72.5 µg/ml, respectively, and induced DNA fragmentation in the HT-29 cell 
line at a concentration of 65 µg/ml.
CONCLUSION: The alkaloid fraction of E. coronaria exhibited significant 
cytotoxicity. Alkaloids such as ervatamine, apparicine and coronaridine that 
were earlier reported may be responsible for this activity.
