[Investigation on traditional medicines of Guarany Indio and studies on 
diterpenes from Scoparia dulcis].

[Article in Japanese]

Hayashi T(1).

Author information:
(1)Graduate School of Medicine and Pharmaceutical Sciences for Research, 
University of Toyama, Toyama, Japan. hayashi9@pha.u-toyama.ac.jp

In interviews on the traditional herbal medicines of Tupi-Guarany Indians at the 
herbal market of Asuncion and questionnaire from their users, it was clarified 
that various useful medicinal plants are available in Paraguay and most of them 
are generally used without drying. In the search for bioactive substances from 
those plants, a β-glucuronidase-inhibitory diterpene called scoparic acid A (SA) 
was isolated from Scoparia dulcis L. together with scoparic acid B, scoparic 
acid C, and the aphidicolin-like tetracyclic diterpenes scopadulcic acid A (SDA) 
and scopadulcic acid B (SDB). HPLC analysis of diterpenes in the individual 
plants of Paraguayan and Asian S. dulcis revealed the presence of three 
chemotypes based on major component, i.e., SA type, SDB type, and SDX type 
containing mainly scopadiol and scopadulciol (SDC). SA and SDB were elucidated 
to be mainly biosynthesized in the leaves via 2-C-methyl-D-erythritol- 
4-phosphate pathway, and a leaf organ culture system containing methyl jasmonate 
10 µM was found to enhance the production of diterpenes by activation of 
Ca-signal transduction systems such as calmodulin and protein kinase C. On the 
other hand, SDB and SDC were found to show multifaceted pharmacological effects 
such as inhibitory effects on gastric acid excretion, bone resorption, 
replication of herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1), etc. In addition, SDC was 
suggested to be applicable to cancer gene therapy using ganciclovir or acyclovir 
and the HSV-1 thymidine kinase gene called the suicide gene.
