
Extraction, fractionation and re-fractionation of Artemisia nilagirica for 
anticancer activity and HPLC-ESI-QTOF-MS/MS determination.

Sahu N(1), Meena S(2), Shukla V(3), Chaturvedi P(4), Kumar B(5), Datta D(6), 
Arya KR(7).

Author information:
(1)Ethnobotany Division CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow 226031, 
UP, India. Electronic address: neha.4sahu@gmail.com.
(2)Biochemistry, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow 226031, UP, 
India. Electronic address: sanjeev.meena@cdri.res.in.
(3)Sophisticated Analytical Instrument Facilities, CSIR-Central Drug Research 
Institute, Lucknow 226031, UP, India. Electronic address: 
vijayavaidehyshukla@gmail.com.
(4)Biochemistry, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow 226031, UP, 
India. Electronic address: priyankcdri@gmail.com.
(5)Sophisticated Analytical Instrument Facilities, CSIR-Central Drug Research 
Institute, Lucknow 226031, UP, India. Electronic address: 
brijesh_kumar@cdri.res.in.
(6)Biochemistry, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow 226031, UP, 
India. Electronic address: dipak.datta@cdri.res.in.
(7)Ethnobotany Division CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute, Lucknow 226031, 
UP, India. Electronic address: aryakr@rediffmail.com.

ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: Medicinal plants used in traditional medicines 
are affordable, easily accessible, safer, less toxic and considered as a rich or 
efficient source of bioactive molecules for modern therapeutics. Artemisia 
nilagirica (AR) has a long history of use in Indian traditional medicine to 
combat a wide variety of diseases including cancer.
AIM OF THE STUDY: Considering the vast potential of traditional healing plants 
to deliver safer, less toxic and efficient chemotherapeutics, we have examined 
anticancer activity of ethanolic extract, bioactive fractions and sub-fractions 
of AR against different human cancer cell lines along with their phytochemical 
analysis to understand the insights of novel anticancer activities for further 
preclinical studies.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Fresh plant material of AR was procured from the wild, 
dried and ground. The grinded materials was extracted in ethanol (AR-01) and 
fractionated into butanol (AR-02), ethyl acetate (AR-03), hexane (AR-04) and 
water (AR-05). The cytotoxicity was evaluated against three different human 
cancer cell lines, i.e. colon (DLD-1), lung (A-549), and breast (MCF-7) using 
Sulforhodamine B (SRB) assay along with non-cancerous VERO cells as control and 
doxorubicin (DOX) as positive control. As we observed strong cytotoxicity of 
AR-03 and AR-04 fractions against tested cells and marked cytotoxic effects 
particularly in colon cancer cell lines, we further re-fractionated, AR-03 into 
(AR-03A, AR-03B, AR-03C, AR-03D, AR-03E) and AR-04 into (AR-04A, AR-04B, AR-04C) 
sub-fractions by column chromatography and investigated against the same panel 
of cell lines in addition to one more colon cancer cell line (HT-29). 
Phytochemical analysis was performed through HPLC-ESI-QTOF-MS/MS fragmentation.
RESULTS: Ethyl acetate (AR-03) and hexane (AR-04) fractions were found to be the 
most cytotoxic against all the tested cell lines. Further, AR-03E and AR-04A 
sub-fractions were found more specific cytotoxic selectively against DLD-1 
cancer cell lines at 100µg/ml concentration. HPLC-ESI-QTOF-MS/MS determination 
revealed the presence of 17 compounds in AR-01. Among them, 4 compounds were 
reported for the first time in this species. However, 3 identified compounds 
(artemorin, β-santonin and caryophyllene oxide) in AR-03E sub-fraction were 
commonly present in each bioactive fraction and may be considered as potential 
and safest cytotoxic agents for anticancer activity.
CONCLUSIONS: Experimental evidences reported in this paper for anticancer 
activity validate the traditional wisdom of Artemisia nilagirica as an 
anticancer herbal drug. To our knowledge, this is our first novel observation of 
cytotoxicity and selectivity of ethyl acetate and hexane sub-fraction of AR-01 
i.e. AR-03E and AR-04A respectively against DLD-1 human cancer cell lines. 
HPLC-ESI-QTOF-MS/MS determination attributes the identification of cytotoxic 
compounds which may be used for further preclinical studies.