Neem Limonoids as Anticancer Agents: Modulation of Cancer Hallmarks and 
Oncogenic Signaling.

Nagini S(1).

Author information:
(1)Faculty of Science, Department of Biochemistry and Biotechnology, Annamalai 
University, Annamalainagar, Tamil Nadu, India. Electronic address: 
s_nagini@yahoo.com.

Neem (Azadirachta indica A. Juss) is one of the most versatile medicinal plants, 
widely distributed in the Indian subcontinent. Neem is a rich source of 
limonoids that are endowed with potent medicinal properties predominantly 
antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, and anticancer activities. Azadirachtin, 
gedunin, and nimbolide are more extensively investigated relative to other neem 
limonoids. Accumulating evidence indicates that the anticancer effects of neem 
limonoids are mediated through the inhibition of hallmark capabilities of cancer 
such as cell proliferation, apoptosis evasion, inflammation, invasion, and 
angiogenesis. The neem limonoids have been demonstrated to target oncogenic 
signaling kinases and transcription factors chiefly, NF-κB, Wnt/β-catenin, 
PI3K/Akt, MAPK, and JAK/STAT signaling pathways. Neem limonoids that target 
multiple pathways that are aberrant in cancer are ideal candidates for cancer 
chemoprevention and therapy.