Cytotoxic and HIV-1 enzyme inhibitory activities of Red Sea marine organisms.

Ellithey MS, Lall N, Hussein AA, Meyer D(1).

Author information:
(1)Department of Biochemistry, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, 0002, South 
Africa. Debra.Meyer@up.ac.za.

BACKGROUND: Cancer and HIV/AIDS are two of the greatest public health and 
humanitarian challenges facing the world today. Infection with HIV not only 
weakens the immune system leading to AIDS and increasing the risk of 
opportunistic infections, but also increases the risk of several types of 
cancer. The enormous biodiversity of marine habitats is mirrored by the 
molecular diversity of secondary metabolites found in marine animals, plants and 
microbes which is why this work was designed to assess the anti-HIV and 
cytotoxic activities of some marine organisms of the Red Sea.
METHODS: The lipophilic fractions of methanolic extracts of thirteen marine 
organisms collected from the Red Sea (Egypt) were screened for cytotoxicity 
against two human cancer cell lines; leukaemia (U937) and cervical cancer (HeLa) 
cells. African green monkey kidney cells (Vero) were used as normal 
non-malignant control cells. The extracts were also tested for their inhibitory 
activity against HIV-1 enzymes, reverse transcriptase (RT) and protease (PR).
RESULTS: Cytotoxicity results showed strong activity of the Cnidarian Litophyton 
arboreum against U-937 (IC50; 6.5 μg/ml ±2.3) with a selectivity index (SI) of 
6.45, while the Cnidarian Sarcophyton trochliophorum showed strong activity 
against HeLa cells (IC50; 5.2 μg/ml ±1.2) with an SI of 2.09. Other species 
showed moderate to weak cytotoxicity against both cell lines. Two extracts 
showed potent inhibitory activity against HIV-1 protease; these were the 
Cnidarian jelly fish Cassiopia andromeda (IC50; 0.84 μg/ml ±0.05) and the red 
algae Galaxura filamentosa (2.6 μg/ml ±1.29). It is interesting to note that the 
most active extracts against HIV-1 PR, C. andromeda and G. filamentosa showed no 
cytotoxicity in the three cell lines at the highest concentration tested 
(100 μg/ml).
CONCLUSION: The strong cytotoxicity of the soft corals L. arboreum and S. 
trochliophorum as well as the anti-PR activity of the jelly fish C. andromeda 
and the red algae G. filamentosa suggests the medicinal potential of crude 
extracts of these marine organisms.

