New cytochalasin from Rosellinia sanctae-cruciana, an endophytic fungus of 
Albizia lebbeck.

Sharma N(1)(2), Kushwaha M(1), Arora D(1)(2), Jain S(3), Singamaneni V(3), 
Sharma S(4), Shankar R(5), Bhushan S(4)(6), Gupta P(2)(3), Jaglan S(1)(2).

Author information:
(1)Microbial Biotechnology Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative 
Medicine, Jammu, India.
(2)Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research (AcSIR), Jammu, India.
(3)Natural Product Chemistry Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative 
Medicine, Jammu, India.
(4)Cancer Pharmacology Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine, 
Jammu, India.
(5)Bioorganic Chemistry Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine, 
Jammu, India.
(6)Indian Pharmacopoeia Commission, Ghaziabad, India.

AIM: To explore the potential of Rosellinia sanctae-cruciana an endophytic 
fungus associated with Albizia lebbeck for pharmaceutically important cytotoxic 
compounds.
METHODS AND RESULTS: One novel cytochalasin, named jammosporin A (1) and four 
known analogues (2-5) were isolated from the culture of the endophytic fungus R. 
sanctae-cruciana, harboured from the leaves of the medicinal plant A. lebbeck. 
Their structures were elucidated by extensive spectroscopic analyses including 
one-dimensional and two-dimensional nuclear magnetic resonance data along with 
MS data and by comparison with literature reports. In preliminary screening the 
ethyl acetate extract of the fungal culture was tested for cytotoxic activity 
against a panel of four cancer cell lines (MOLT-4, A549, MIA PaCa-2 and 
MDA-MB-231), and found to be active against MOLT-4 with an IC50 value of 
10 μg ml-1 . Owing to the remarkable cytotoxic activity of the extract the 
isolated compounds (1-5) were evaluated for their cytototoxicity against the 
MOLT-4 cell line by MTT assay. Interestingly, compounds 1-2, 4 and 5 showed 
considerable cytotoxic potential against the human leukaemia cancer cell line 
(MOLT-4) with IC50 values of 20·0, 10·0, 8·0 and 6·0 μmol l-1 , respectively, 
while compound 3 showed an IC50 value of 25 μmol l-1 . This is the first report 
of the existence of this class of secondary metabolites in R. sanctae-cruciana 
fungus.
CONCLUSION: This study discovered a novel compound, named jammosporin A, 
isolated for the first time from R. sanctae-cruciana, an endophytic fungus of A. 
lebbeck with anticancer activity against the MOLT-4 cell line.
SIGNIFICANCE AND IMPACT OF THE STUDY: Rosellinia sanctae-cruciana represents an 
interesting source of a new compound with bioactive potential as a therapeutic 
agent against a human leukaemia cancer cell line (MOLT-4).