Synthesis of cyclic 1,9-acetal derivatives of forskolin and their bioactivity 
evaluation.

Ponnam D(1), Shilpi S(2), Srinivas KV(3), Suiab L(2), Alam S(4), Amtul Z(5), 
Arigari NK(1), Jonnala KK(6), Siddiqui L(2), Dubey V(2), Tiwari AK(5), 
Balasubramanian S(7), Khan F(4).

Author information:
(1)Natural Product Chemistry, CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic 
Plants- Research Centre, Boduppal, Hyderabad 500092, Telangana, India.
(2)Molecular Bioprospection Department, CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and 
Aromatic Plants, Kukrail Picnic Spot Road, Lucknow 226015, UP, India.
(3)Natural Product Chemistry, CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic 
Plants- Research Centre, Boduppal, Hyderabad 500092, Telangana, India. 
Electronic address: kvnssrinivas@yahoo.co.in.
(4)Metabolic & Structural Biology Department, CSIR-Central Institute of 
Medicinal and Aromatic Plants, Kukrail Picnic Spot Road, Lucknow 226015, UP, 
India.
(5)Medicinal Chemistry and Pharmacology Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of 
Chemical Technology, Uppal Road, Hyderabad 500007, Telangana, India.
(6)Natural Product Chemistry, CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic 
Plants- Research Centre, Boduppal, Hyderabad 500092, Telangana, India. 
Electronic address: koteshkumarj@yahoo.com.
(7)CSIR-Centre for X-ray Crystallography, Indian Institute of Chemical 
Technology, Uppal Road, Hyderabad 500007, Telangana, India.

A new series of 1,9-acetals of forskolin were synthesized by treating with 
aromatic and aliphatic aldehydes using Ceric ammonium nitrate as catalyst and 
evaluated for anticancer and α-glucosidase inhibition activities. Among the 
synthesized compounds 2a, 2b and 3a showed potential cytotoxic activity towards 
human cancer cell lines MCF-7 (Human Breast Adenocarcinoma), MDA-MB (Human 
Breast Carcinoma), HeLa (Human Cervix Adenocarcinoma), A498 (Human Kidney 
Carcinoma), K562 (Human Erythromyeloblastoid leukemia), SH-SY5Y (Human 
Neuroblastoma), Hek293 (Human Embryonic Kidney) and WRL68 (Human Hepatic) with 
IC50 values ranging between 0.95 and 47.96 μg/ml. Osmotic fragility test 
revealed compound 3a as non-toxic to human erythrocytes at the tested 
concentrations of 50 and 100 μg/ml. Compounds 1g (IC50 value 0.76 μg/ml) and 1p 
(IC50 value 0.74 μg/ml) significantly inhibited α-glucosidase in in vitro 
system. In silico based docking, ADME and toxicity risk assessment studies also 
showed discernible α-glucosidase activity for compounds 1g, 1p compared to 
standard acarbose.
