Bioactive hydroperoxyl cembranoids from the Red Sea soft coral Sarcophyton 
glaucum.

Hegazy ME(1), Gamal Eldeen AM, Shahat AA, Abdel-Latif FF, Mohamed TA, Whittlesey 
BR, Paré PW.

Author information:
(1)Chemistry of Medicinal Plants Department, and Center of Excellence for 
Advanced Sciences, National Research Centre, El-Tahrir Street, Dokki, Giza 
12622, Egypt.

A chemical investigation of an ethyl acetate extract of the Red Sea soft coral 
Sarcophyton glaucum has led to the isolation of two peroxide diterpenes, 11(S) 
hydroperoxylsarcoph-12(20)-ene (1), and 12(S)-hydroperoxylsarcoph-10-ene (2), as 
well as 8-epi-sarcophinone (3). In addition to these three new compounds, two 
known structures were identified including: ent-sarcophine (4) and sarcophine 
(5). Structures were elucidated by spectroscopic analysis, with the relative 
configuration of 1 and 2 confirmed by X-ray diffraction. Isolated compounds were 
found to be inhibitors of cytochrome P₄₅₀ 1A activity as well as inducers of 
glutathione S-transferases (GST), quinone reductase (QR), and epoxide hydrolase 
(mEH) establishing chemo-preventive and tumor anti-initiating activity for these 
characterized metabolites.