Effects of Ginkgo biloba extract on the apoptosis of oxygen and glucose-deprived 
SH-SY5Y cells and its mechanism.

Ba XH(1), Min LQ(1).

Author information:
(1)Department of Neurology, the First Affiliated Hospital, Liaoning Medical 
University, Jinzhou 121001, China ; Key Laboratory of Brain and Spinal Cord 
Injury in Liaoning Province, Jinzhou 121001, China.

OBJECTIVE: The aim was to observe the effects of the extract of Ginkgo biloba 
(EGb761) on the apoptosis of oxygen and glucose-deprived (OGD) human 
neuroblastoma cells (SH-SY5Y) cells and explore its mechanism.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: SH-SY5Y cells were divided into normal control group, OGD 
group, OGD for 4 h and EGb761-pretreated groups including very low-concentration 
(20 μg/ml), low-concentration group (25 μg/ml), moderate-concentration group (50 
μg/ml) and high-concentration group (100 μg/ml). Twenty four hours after 
reoxygenation, cell viability was determined with 3-[4, 
5-dimehyl-2-thiazolyl]-2, 5-diphenyl-2H-tetrazolium bromide assay, apoptosis 
rate was detected with annexin V-fluorescein isothiocyanate/propidium iodide 
double staining flow cytometry and the protein level of apoptosis-inducing 
factor (AIF) was observed with immunofluorescence technique in each group.
RESULTS: Cell viability was significantly lower in OGD group than in 
EGb761-pretreated groups, especially in moderate-concentration group (50 μg/ml) 
(P < 0.005). Apoptosis rate was significantly lower in EGb761-pretreated groups 
than in OGD group (P < 0.001). Immunofluorescent staining showed that there was 
AIF nuclear translocation in both EGb761-pretreated groups and OGD group, but 
AIF nuclear translocation was less in EGb761-pretreated groups than in OGD 
group.
CONCLUSION: EGb761 can reduce the apoptosis of OGD SH-SY5Y cells probably 
through inhibiting AIF nuclear translocation. This study provides a theoretical 
basis for the application of EGb761 in clinical practice.
