Atmospheric particulate matters in an Indian urban area: Health implications 
from potentially hazardous elements, cytotoxicity, and genotoxicity studies.

Islam N(1), Dihingia A(2), Khare P(3), Saikia BK(4).

Author information:
(1)Polymer Petroleum and Coal Chemistry Group, Materials Science and Technology 
Division, CSIR-North East Institute of Science and Technology, Jorhat, 785006, 
Assam, India; Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research, CSIR-NEIST Campus, 
Jorhat, 785006, India.
(2)Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research, CSIR-NEIST Campus, Jorhat, 
785006, India; Biotechnology Group, Biological Science and Technology Division, 
CSIR-North East Institute of Science and Technology, Jorhat, 785006, Assam, 
India.
(3)Agronomy and Soil Science Division, CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and 
Aromatic Plants, Lucknow, 226015, Uttar Pradesh, India.
(4)Polymer Petroleum and Coal Chemistry Group, Materials Science and Technology 
Division, CSIR-North East Institute of Science and Technology, Jorhat, 785006, 
Assam, India; Academy of Scientific and Innovative Research, CSIR-NEIST Campus, 
Jorhat, 785006, India. Electronic address: bksaikia@neist.res.in.

The nature of the atmospheric particulate matters (PMs) varies depending on 
their sizes and their origin from different activities in the background 
environment. These PMs are associated with potentially hazardous elements (PHEs) 
such as organic compounds (e.g. Polyaromatic Hydrocarbons) that can be harmful 
to health. The main objective of this work is the identification and 
investigation of the toxicological aspects of PHEs in PMs during pre-monsoon and 
post-monsoon season in an urban area of Northeast region (NER) of India. In the 
course of the study, the 24 -hs average concentrations of PMs were detected to 
be more than two-times higher than the Indian standard limit (NAAQ, category) 
which indicates poor air quality in both the seasons around the sampling sites. 
This study demonstrates that the concentrations of PM-bound PAHs are mutagenic 
and that the Excess Cancer Risks exceed the USEPA standard limits. PMs cause 
cytotoxicity and can also induce genotoxicity to human health analyzed by cell 
culture and gel electrophoresis. This study helps to promote research to 
evaluate the PMs bound PHEs toxicity in diverse human cell lines and also their 
relationship with climatic factors as well as quantitative source apportionment 
for mitigation purposes.