Withania somnifera chemotype NMITLI 101R significantly increases the efficacy of 
antileishmanial drugs by generating strong IFN-γ and IL-12 mediated immune 
responses in Leishmania donovani infected hamsters.

Tripathi CD(1), Kushawaha PK(2), Sangwan RS(3), Mandal C(4), Misra-Bhattacharya 
S(1), Dube A(5).

Author information:
(1)Parasitology Division, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute (CDRI), Lucknow, 
226001, India.
(2)Parasitology Division, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute (CDRI), Lucknow, 
226001, India; Centre for Biochemistry and Microbial Sciences, Central 
University of Punjab, Bathinda, 151001, India.
(3)Metabolic and Structural Biology Division, CSIR-Central Institute of 
Medicinal and Aromatic Plants (CIMAP), Lucknow, 226015, India.
(4)Cancer Biology and Inflammatory Disorder Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of 
Chemical Biolgy (IICB), Kolkata, 700032, India.
(5)Parasitology Division, CSIR-Central Drug Research Institute (CDRI), Lucknow, 
226001, India. Electronic address: anuradhadube@gmail.com.

BACKGROUND: Withania somnifera (L.) Dunal (Solanaceae), commonly known as 
Ashwagandha, is one of the most important medicinal plant in the traditional 
Indian medical systems. Pharmacological studies have established that root 
extracts of W. somnifera contain several bioactive constituents called 
withanolides. The plant has long been used for its several beneficial properties 
and recently as an immunomodulator.
HYPOTHESIS/PURPOSE: A combination therapy including a potential and safe 
immunostimulant with lower doses of effective drug, which can reduce the 
parasitic burden and simultaneously can produce an enhancement of adaptive 
immunity, has proven to be significantly a more effective approach than 
immunotherapy or drug therapy alone.
STUDY DESIGN: Evaluation of the immunostimulatory effect of W. somnifera 
chemotype NMITLI 101R when used in combination with ED50 doses of 
antileishmanial drugs in Leishmania donovani infected hamsters.
METHODS: Infected animals were administered with chemotype 
101R(30mg/kg × 15 days) either alone or in combination with ED50 doses of 
miltefosine (10mg/kg × 5 days), paromomycin (30mg/kg × 5 days) or amphotericin B 
(0.5mg/kg × 5 days). The treated animals were euthanized on days 30 and 60 
post-treatment (p.t.) and checked for parasite clearance, delayed type 
hypersensitivity (DTH) response, cytokine and inducible nitric oxide synthase 
levels by real-time PCR, nitric oxide (NO) production, reactive oxygen species 
(ROS) generation, lymphoproliferative and antibody responses.
RESULTS: The group of animals that received 101R and ED50 dose of miltefosine 
showed optimum inhibition of parasite multiplication (∼98%) by day 60 p.t. 
followed by the group that received 101R plus paromomycin (∼94%) and 101R plus 
amphotericin B (∼93%). The efficacy was well supported by the increased 
inducible NO synthase mRNA transcript, strong IFN-γand IL-12 mediated Th1 immune 
responses and significantly suppressed levels of Th2 cytokines (IL-4, IL-10 and 
TGF-β). Additionally, same therapy also induced significant increase in the 
level of NO production, ROS generation, Leishmania specific IgG2 antibody along 
with profound DTH and strong T-cell responses as compared with all the other 
treated groups.
CONCLUSION: Our results suggest that combination of chemotype 101R with ED50 
doses of antileishmanial drugs may provide a promising alternative for the cure 
of visceral leishmaniasis with significant restoration of the host immune 
response.

