Antiproliferative activity and standardization of Tecomella undulata bark 
extract on K562 cells.

Ravi A(1), Mallika A, Sama V, Begum AS, Khan RS, Reddy BM.

Author information:
(1)G Pulla Reddy College of Pharmacy, Mehdipatnam, Hyderabad 500 028, AP, India. 
ravi_alvala@yahoo.co.in

ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: The bark of Tecomella undulata is primarily used 
in the treatment of syphilis, painful swellings and cancer by traditional 
healers. Also, it is claimed to be useful in treating urinary discharges, 
enlargement of spleen, leucorrhoea, leukoderma, tumors, liver disorders, 
gonorrhea, gout and promotes wound healing in Indian traditional system of 
medicine.
AIM: To establish a scientific validation for the antitumor effects of Tecomella 
undulata bark and explore the mechanistic pathway in chronic myeloid leukemia 
cell line, K562. The study was further extended to standardize the extract using 
quercetin as biomarker.
METHODS: Induction of apoptosis by chloroform extract of Tecomella undulata bark 
(CTUB) was determined by MTT, Annexin V and caspase activation assays. The cell 
cycle analysis was done by flow cytometer and nuclear staining by DAPI. The 
standardization of the extract was performed through reverse phase-HPLC method 
under PDA detection.
RESULT: Results clearly showed the induction of apoptosis by CTUB in K562 cells. 
The effect was found to be dose dependent, having IC(50) of 30 μg/ml with 
activation of FAS, FADD, caspase 8, caspase 3/7 and fragmentation of DNA. The 
bioactive CTUB was determined to possess 0.03% (w/w) of quercetin.
CONCLUSION: The investigation clearly demonstrated the potential antitumor 
effect of CTUB, thereby validating the traditional claim. Quercetin, known to 
have anticancer activity is being reported and quantified for the first time 
from the bark of Tecomella undulata.