Modulation of liver function, antioxidant responses, insulin resistance and 
glucose transport by Oroxylum indicum stem bark in STZ induced diabetic rats.

Singh J(1), Kakkar P.

Author information:
(1)Herbal Research Section, CSIR-Indian Institute of Toxicology Research, Post 
Box No. 80, Mahatma Gandhi Marg, Lucknow 226001, UP, India.

A decoction of stem bark of Oroxylum indicum Vent. (OI) is taken (2-3 times/day) 
by the tribal people of Sikkim, India to treat diabetes but scientific 
validation of its overall potential is lacking. Present study was aimed to 
assess in vitro antihyperglycemic activity of standardized OI extract using 
inhibition of α-glucosidase, BSA glycation and enhancement of insulin 
sensitivity. Antidiabetic and antioxidant modulatory effects of OI extract along 
with the blood biomarkers of toxic response were studied in streptozotocin (STZ) 
induced diabetic rats. In vitro analysis showed strong antioxidant capacity of 
OI -and potential to inhibit BSA glycation and α-glucosidase activity which was 
comparable to standard counterparts. Extract also improved insulin sensitivity 
in mature 3T3-L1 adipocytes. In vivo effects of OI extract (oral 250 mg/kg 
b.wt.) on STZ induced type II diabetic rats normalized the antioxidant status 
(p≤0.01). Analysis of blood biomarkers of toxic response indicated its safety. 
Lowering of total cholesterol and HDL levels (p≤0.05) and restoration of 
glycated Hb (p≤0.01) were also found in OI treated diabetic rats. HOMA-IR, 
QUICKI analysis along with area under the curve analysis showed the capacity of 
OI extract to enhance the insulin sensitivity significantly (p≤0.01) which was 
confirmed by increased GLUT-4 translocation in skeletal muscles.