Evaluation of anti-osteoarthritic activity of Vigna mungo in papain induced 
osteoarthritis model.

Patel DV(1), Sawant MG(2), Kaur G(1).

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacology, SPP School of Pharmacy and Technology Management, 
Vile Parle (West), India.
(2)Department of Toxicology, Haffkine Institute, Mumbai, Maharashtra, India.

AIM: This study was carried out to evaluate the effect of Vigna mungo 
hydroalcoholic extract (VMHA) by papain induced osteoarthritis (OA) in the rat 
model.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: OA was induced by intra-articular injection of papain (4% 
w/v) along with cysteine (0.03 M) on day 1, 4 and 7 in rats and VMHA was 
administered orally in three doses (100, 200 and 400 mg/kg) after last papain 
injection. The anti-osteoarthritic activity was evaluated by measuring knee 
joint diameter, grip strength, locomotion activity and hanging time. 
Histopathological analysis and acute toxicity study were also performed.
RESULTS: VMHA improved inflammatory condition with all the doses, but 
significant (P < 0.05) attenuation of inflammation was present only with 400 
mg/kg dose. The grip strength, locomotion activity and hanging time were also 
significantly (P < 0.05) improved at dose level of 100 mg/kg however other two 
doses (200 mg/kg and 400 mg/kg) were not found to be effective. VMHA did not 
show any mortality or any toxic clinical signs after oral administration of 2 
g/kg dose.
CONCLUSION: VMHA improved arthritic condition by significantly reducing pain and 
inflammation.