Preliminary evaluation of anti-inflammatory and anti-arthritic activity of S. 
lappa, A. speciosa and A. aspera.

Gokhale AB(1), Damre AS, Kulkami KR, Saraf MN.

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacology, Bombay College of Pharmacy, Kalina, Mumbai, 
India.

Saussurea lappa, Argyreia speciosa and Achyranthes aspera are well known Indian 
medicinal plants used in the indigenous systems of medicine for the treatment of 
inflammatory conditions. The ethanolic extracts of the plants at the doses of 
50, 100 and 200 mg/kg, p.o. were screened for their effect on acute and chronic 
inflammation induced in mice and rats. S. lappa and A. speciosa were found to 
significantly inhibit paw edema induced by carrageenan and Freund's complete 
adjuvant and to prevent accumulation of inflammatory cells in 
carrageenan-induced peritonitis at doses of 50-200 mg/kg. A. aspera inhibited 
these inflammatory responses at doses of 100-200 mg/kg. The studies reveal that 
the ethanolic extracts of S. lappa, A. speciosa and A. aspera possess 
anti-inflammatory and anti-arthritic activity and support the rationale behind 
the traditional use of these plants in inflammatory conditions.
