Clinical toxicity study of Semecarpus anacardium Linn. f.

Murty GK.

PIP: Semecarpus anacardium was administered to 266 cases in 3 formulations: 
Amrit Bhallatak (186 cases), RB 3 (48 cases), and Garsin (32 cases). The Amrit 
Bhallatak is a compound formulation containing extract of both the cotyledons 
and the pericarp of the fruit of Semecarpus anacardium. RB3 is composed of the 
whole cotyledon (300 mg); the daily dose of cotyledons was 3.6 g. Garsin 
contained 200 g of cotyledons. The extract is derived by separating the oil by a 
physical process. The daily dosage of Amrit Bhallatak was 10 g/day, that of 
Garsin, 2.4 g/day. No toxicity or side effects were observed. The therapeutic 
value of Semecarpus anacardium in arthropathies, atopic dermatitis, leucoderma, 
leprosy, hypothyroidism, oligospermia, and azoospermia and its value as an oral 
contraceptive have been studied. The most significant effect was on the ovaries 
and testes. The drug probably acts via the hypophysics. Out of 266 patients, 189 
were men, 77 women between 30-45 years of age. The treatment was restricted to 
internal medication by mouth. No external contact or application of the drug was 
applied. Of the 77 women treated with the drug, 41 were followed up after 
treatment. 12 had become pregnant and none showed any teratogenecity.