Traditional medicinal plant use in Loja province, Southern Ecuador.

Bussmann RW(1), Sharon D.

Author information:
(1)University of Hawaii, Lyon Arboretum, 3860 Manoa Rd,, Honolulu, HI 96822, 
USA. bussmann@hawaii.edu

This paper examines the traditional use of medicinal plants in Loja province, 
Southern Ecuador.Two hundred fifteen plant species were collected, identified 
and their vernacular names and traditional uses recorded. This number of species 
indicates that the healers, market vendors and members of the public interviewed 
still have a very high knowledge of plants in their surroundings, which can be 
seen as a reflection of the knowledge of the population in general. However, the 
area represents only an outlier of the larger Northern Peruvian cultural area, 
where more than 500 species of plants are used medicinally, indicating that in 
Ecuador much of the original plant knowledge has already been lost.Most plant 
species registered are only used medicinally, and only a few species have any 
other use (construction, fodder, food). The highest number of species is used 
for the treatment of "magical" (psychosomatic) ailments (39 species), followed 
by respiratory disorders (34), problems of the urinary tract (28), Fever/Malaria 
(25), Rheumatism (23) and nervous system problems (20).