Effects of Tinospora cordifolia (Menispermaceae) on the proliferation, 
osteogenic differentiation and mineralization of osteoblast model systems in 
vitro.

Abiramasundari G(1), Sumalatha KR, Sreepriya M.

Author information:
(1)Department of Microbiology and Biotechnology, Bangalore University, Jnana 
Bharathi Campus, Bangalore 560056, Karnataka, India.

ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: Ancient Indian ayurvedic literature prescribes 
Tinospora cordifolia as a remedy to rheumatoid arthritis, inflammatory and 
allied diseases of musculo skeletal system.
AIM: To investigate the effects of the alcoholic extract of Tinospora cordifolia 
(TC) on the proliferation, differentiation and mineralization of bone like 
matrix on osteoblast model systems in vitro and hence its possible use as a 
potential anti-osteoporotic agent.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Two in vitro osteoblast model systems were used in the 
study viz., human osteoblast-like cells MG-63 and primary osteoblast cells 
isolated from femur of rats. Cell growth and viability was assessed by standard 
colorimetric assays like MTT assay. The cell differentiation into osteoblastic 
lineage was evaluated by the activities of bone marker alkaline phosphatase. The 
effect of the extract on matrix mineralization was assessed by alizarin red-s 
staining and Von kossa staining. Cell morphology was studied by phase contrast 
microscopy and light microscopy (Giemsa/crystal violet staining).
RESULTS: Results indicate that the alcoholic extract of TC at a dosage of 
25μg/ml stimulated the growth of osteoblasts, increased the differentiation of 
cells into osteoblastic lineage and increased the mineralization of bone like 
matrix on both the osteoblast model systems used in the study. Cell morphology 
studies clearly indicated the increase in cell numbers and absence of adverse 
change in the cell morphology on treatment with the extract.
CONCLUSION: TC extract has a potential influence on osteogenesis and hence its 
use could be explored as a potential anti-osteoporotic agent.
