Amaranthus viridis (Amaranthaceae) widely distributed all over the 
world, growing under a wide range of climatic conditions and has been utilized 
as a medicinal herb in traditional Ayurvedic medicine as antipyretic agents, 
also for the treatment of inflammation, ulcer, diabetic, asthma and 
hyperlipidemia. The aim of the study was designed to evaluate the chemical 
composition and antioxidant and biological properties of different fractions 
obtained from A. viridis.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Four different extracts of A. viridis were prepared using 
aqueous, methanol, chloroform, and hexane and investigated their antioxidant 
potential using free radical scavenging activities such as 
2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH), 
2,2'-azinobis-3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid (ABTS), and nitric oxide 
(NO) radical scavenging activity, as well as metal chelating activity. In 
addition, antityrosinase and antigenotoxicity properties were also evaluated by 
the standard in vitro methods. Finally, the active methanolic extract (ME) was 
investigated for identifying the phenolic compounds using UPLC-MS/MS.
RESULTS: In the present study, chlorogenic acid, gulonic acid, and kaempferol 
were found to be the major components responsible for the antioxidant activity 
of A. viridis extract as evidenced from UPLC-MS/MS. Furthermore, the ME of A. 
viridis revealed excellent antioxidant activities such as DPPH radical 
scavenging activity (IC50= 47.23 ± 0.66 μg/mL), NO radical scavenging activity 
(IC50= 64.33 ± 2.01 μg/mL), hydrogen peroxide (H2O2) radical scavenging activity 
(IC50= 33.21 ± 3.3 μg/mL), ABTS radical scavenging activity (IC50= 47.61 ± 1.31 
μg/mL), metal chelating activity (IC50= 32.1 ± 1.11 μg/mL), as well as lipid 
peroxidation inhibiting activity (IC50= 112 ± 1.21 μg/mL). Furthermore, ME 
revealed that the protective effects of extract were observed on H2O2-induced 
DNA damages with alkaline comet assay.
CONCLUSIONS: Taken together, the study concluded that the promising antioxidant 
capacities of A. viridis extract can further be utilized in various 
agricultural, pharmaceutical, and food applications.