Anti-inflammatory, analgesic and antipyretic properties of Thespesia populnea 
Soland ex. Correa seed extracts and its fractions in animal models.

Shah AS(1), Alagawadi KR.

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, KLEU's College of Pharmacy, Belgaum, 
Karnataka, India. amol2473@indiatimes.com

ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: Thespesia populnea Sol. ex Correa (Malvaceae) is 
commonly known as "Indian tulip tree". The plant has been used as an astringent, 
antibacterial, anti-inflammatory, antinociceptive and hepatoprotective in Indian 
system of traditional medicine.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Thespesia populnea seeds were successively extracted by 
soxhlet extraction using petroleum ether (40-60 °C) (TPO) and ethanol (TPE). 
Unsaponifiable matter (TPOUM) and fatty acids were separated from seed oil. A 
GC-MS analysis of fatty acid methyl esters was carried out. Ethanolic extract 
was fractionated using CHCl(3), EtOAc, n-BuOH and H(2)O. Acute arthritis was 
induced by sub-plantar injection of carrageenan into the left hind paw of rats. 
The paw volume was measured using plethysmometer. Analgesic activity was 
assessed by heat induced pains (tail immersion model) and antipyretic activity 
assessed using brewers yeast-induced pyrexia model.
RESULTS: Oral administration of TPO and TPE at 200 and 400 mg/kg b.w. and tested 
fractions at 200mg/kg significantly reduced carrageenan induced paw edema and 
brewers yeast-induced pyrexia. In tail immersion method also extracts and 
fractions showed significant analgesic activity. Amongst all fractions EtOAc 
showed most significant results. TPOUM showed significant anti-inflammatory and 
analgesic activity. GC-MS analyses showed the presence of fourteen fatty acids, 
predominant fatty acids were palmitic and stearic acid.
CONCLUSION: These results highlighted anti-inflammatory, analgesic and 
antipyretic effects of Thespesia populnea seeds.