Umbelliferone β-D-galactopyranoside from Aegle marmelos (L.) corr. an 
ethnomedicinal plant with antidiabetic, antihyperlipidemic and antioxidative 
activity.

Kumar V(1), Ahmed D, Verma A, Anwar F, Ali M, Mujeeb M.

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Faculty of Health Sciences, Sam 
Higginbottom Institute of Agriculture, Technology & Sciences, Allahabad, Uttar 
Pradesh 211007, India. phvikas@gmail.com.

BACKGROUND: Aegle marmelos (L.) Corr. (Rutaceae), commonly known as bael, is 
used to treat fevers, abdomen pain, palpitation of the heart, urinary troubles, 
melancholia, anorexia, dyspepsia, diabetes and diarrhea in Indian traditional 
systems of medicine. The object of the present study was to evaluate the 
antidiabetic, antihyperlipidemic and antioxidant oxidative stress of 
umbelliferone β-D-galactopyranoside (UFG) from stem bark of Aegle marmelos 
Correa. in STZ (streptozotocin) induced diabetic rat.
METHODS: Diabetes was induced in rat by single intraperitoneal injection of STZ 
(60 mg/kg). The rat was divided into the following groups; I - normal control, 
II - diabetic control, III - UFG (10 mg/kg), IV - UFG (20 mg/kg), V - UFG (40 
mg/kg), VI - Glibenclamide (10 mg/kg, p.o., once a daily dose). Diabetes was 
measured by change the level blood glucose, plasma insulin and the oxidative 
stress were assessed in the liver by estimation of the level of antioxidant 
markers i.e. superoxide dismutase (SOD), glutathione peroxidase (GPx), catalase 
(CAT) and Malondialdehyde (MDA) and antihyperlipidemic effect was measured by 
estimation of total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL (low density lipoprotein) 
cholesterol, HDL (high density lipoprotein) cholesterol, VLDL (very low density 
lipoprotein) cholesterol. However in a study, the increased body weight was 
observed and utilization of glucose was in the oral glucose tolerance test.
RESULT: Daily oral administration of different dose of UFG for 28 days showed 
significantly (P < 0.001) decreased in fasting blood glucose level and improve 
plasma insulin level as compared to the diabetic control group. Also it 
significantly (P < 0.001) decreased the level of glycated hemoglobin, 
glucose-6-phosphatase, fructose-1-6-biphosphate and increased the level of 
hexokinase. UFG treatment decreased liver MDA and increased the level of SOD, 
GPx and CAT. UFG treatment of lipids it's increased the level of cholesterol, 
triglycerides, VLDL, LDL cholesterol and decreased the level of HDL cholesterol. 
Histologically, inflammatory cell in blood vessels, intercalated disc, fat 
degeneration and focal necrosis observed in diabetic rat organ but was less 
obvious in UFG treated groups. The mechanism of action of UFG may be due to the 
increased level of pancreatic insulin secretion and effect on the antioxidant 
marker.
CONCLUSION: UFG posses an antidiabetic, antioxidant and antihyperlipidemic 
effect on the STZ induced diabetic rat. Hence it could be the better choice to 
cure the diabetes.