Anti-diabetic effect of a novel N-Trisaccharide isolated from Cucumis 
prophetarum on streptozotocin-nicotinamide induced type 2 diabetic rats.

Kavishankar GB(1), Lakshmidevi N(2).

Author information:
(1)DOS in Microbiology, University of Mysore, Manasagangotri, Mysore 570 006, 
Karnataka, India; DOS in Biochemistry, University of Mysore, Manasagangotri, 
Mysore 570 006, Karnataka, India.
(2)DOS in Microbiology, University of Mysore, Manasagangotri, Mysore 570 006, 
Karnataka, India. Electronic address: nlakshmidevi7@gmail.com.

ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: Cucumis prophetarum (L.) is used in traditional 
Indian medicine for the treatment of inflammation related problems.
AIM OF THE STUDY: The present investigation was designed to study the effect of 
N-Trisaccharide (a new compound isolated from the fruit of C. prophetarum (L.)) 
on hyperglycemia in streptozotocin (STZ)-nicotinamide (NA) induced type 2 
diabetic rats.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Different doses of N-Trisaccharide (25 and 50 mg/kgb.w.) 
were administered once daily for 28 days to STZ-NA induced diabetic rats. Plasma 
insulin and glycogen levels were measured. The activities of hexokinase, 
glucose-6-phosphatase, fructose-1,6-bisphosphatase, glucose-6-phosphate 
dehydrogenase, glycogen synthase and glycogen phosphorylase were measured. 
Further, histological studies on pancreas were also carried out.
RESULTS: The active compound at doses of 25 and 50 mg/kgb.w. given orally for 14 
days showed 47.7% and 69.3% antihyperglycemic activity, respectively. Treatment 
at the same doses for 28 days provided complete protection against STZ-NA 
challenge (65 and 230 mg/kgb.w., respectively), intraperitoneally. 
N-Trisaccharide significantly (p≤0.05) increased the plasma insulin and liver 
glycogen levels in diabetic rats. The altered enzyme activities of carbohydrate 
metabolism in the liver and kidney of the diabetic rats were significantly 
(p≤0.05) improved. Additionally, N-Trisaccharide increased glycogen synthase and 
decreased glycogen phosphorylase activity in diabetic rats. Histological studies 
confirmed an increase in insulin level is due to stimulation of injured 
pancreatic β-cells.
CONCLUSION: The results of the study suggested that N-Trisaccharide possesses 
propitious effect on STZ-NA induced type 2 diabetes, indicating its usefulness 
in diabetes management.
