Evaluation of antioxidant, antibacterial, and antidiabetic potential of two 
traditional medicinal plants of India: Swertia cordata and Swertia chirayita.

Roy P(1), Abdulsalam FI(1), Pandey DK(1), Bhattacharjee A(2), Eruvaram NR(1), 
Malik T(1).

Author information:
(1)Department of Biochemistry, Lovely School of Biotechnology and Biosciences, 
Lovely Professional University Jalandhar, Phagwara, Punjab, India.
(2)Department of Physiology, International Medical School, Management and 
Science University, Shah Alam, Selangor, Malaysia.

BACKGROUND: Swertia cordata and Swertia chirayita are temperate Himalayan 
medicinal plants used as potent herbal drugs in Indian traditional systems of 
medicine (Ayurvedic, Unani and Siddha).
OBJECTIVE: Assessment of Antioxidant, antibacterial, and antidiabetic potential 
of Swertia cordata and Swertia chirayita.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Phytochemicals of methanolic and aqueous extracts of the 
two Swertia species were analyzed. The antioxidant potential of all the extracts 
was assessed by measuring total phenolic content, total flavonoid content and 
free radical scavenging potential was assessed by 1,1-diphenyl-2-picrilhydrazyl 
(DPPH) assay, antibacterial activity was assessed against various pathogenic and 
nonpathogenic bacteria in vitro by Kirby-Bauer agar well diffusion method and 
antidiabetic activity was assessed by α-amylase inhibition.
RESULTS: Methanolic leaf extracts of both the species of Swertia contain 
significant antibacterial as well as anti-diabetic potential, whereas methanolic 
root extracts of both species were found to have potential antioxidant activity. 
However, Swertia chirayita showed better activities than Swertia cordata 
although both species have good reputation in traditional Indian medicine.
CONCLUSION: Both the species are having high medicinal potential in terms of 
their antioxidant, antibacterial and antidiabetic activities. Studies are 
required to further elucidate antioxidant, anti-diabetic and antibacterial 
potentials using various in-vitro, in-vivo biochemical and molecular biology 
techniques.