Chromosomal Fragmentation: A Possible Marker for the Selection of High Gymnemic 
Acid Yielding Accessions of Gymnema sylvestre R. Br.

Verma AK(1), Dhawan SS(2).

Author information:
(1)Central Botanical Laboratory, Botanical Survey of India, AJC Bose Indian 
Botanic Garden, Howrah, West Bengal, India.
(2)Plant Biotechnology Division, CSIR - Central Institute of Medicinal and 
Aromatic Plants, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India.

BACKGROUND: Gymnema sylvestre R. Br. a member of family Asclepiadaceae as 
mentioned in Indian Pharmacopoeia popular among the researchers because of 
stimulatory effect of its phytoconstituent on pancreatic cells and potential to 
treat Type I and II type of diabetes.
OBJECTIVES: Development of cost-effective marker system for the selection of 
high gymnemic acid yielding accessions of G. sylvestre.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Presoaked seeds of Brassica campestris treated with 
different dilutions of gymnemagenin and 10% leaf extract of twenty different 
accessions of G. sylvestre. Root tips of germinated seeds were fixed, and 
chromosomal studies were made by root tip bioassay method.
RESULTS: Exposure of seeds to treatment solutions promotes various types of 
chromosomal anomalies in root meristem, and surprisingly, direct correlation 
between the percentage of chromosomal fragmentation and the percentage of 
gymnemic acid shared by treatment solution were observed.
CONCLUSION: Later finding may be explored for the development of a novel 
methodology or marker system for the selection of high active principle yielding 
accessions of G. sylvestre.
SUMMARY: An experiment was carried out using root tip bioassay method for the 
study of effect of different dilutions of standard gymnemic acid and 10% leaf 
extract of twenty different accessions of Gymnema sylvestre on root tip meristem 
of Brassica campestris. Various types of chromosomal anomalies were observed. Of 
which, percentage of chromosomal fragmentation was showed a direct (∞) 
relationship with the percentage of gymnemic acid shared by treatment solution. 
This interesting result after more and more exploration and revalidation could 
be utilized for the development of a novel methodology for the selection of high 
active principle yielding accessions of G. sylvestre. Abbreviations used: MI: 
Mitotic index; CP: Condensed prophase; CM: Clumped metaphase; MC: Metaphase 
cleft; FR: Fragmentation; AP: Anaphase with persistent nucleolous; LA: Laggard, 
BR: Bridge; BI: Bi-nucleated cell; DA: Disturbed anaphasic polarity.
