Tulsi, Banyan, and Jamun are popular Indian medicinal plants with 
notable hypoglycemic potentials. Now the work reports chemo-profiling of the 
three species with in-vitro screening approach for natural enzyme inhibitors 
(NEIs) against enzymes pathogenic for type 2 diabetes. Further along with the 
chemometrics optimized extraction process technology, phyto-synergistic studies 
of the composite polyherbal blends have also been reported.
OBJECTIVE: Chemometrically optimized extraction procedures, ratios of polyherbal 
composites to achieve phyto-synergistic actions, and in-vitro screening of NEIs 
amongst leaves of Tulsi, Banyan, and Jamun.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: The extraction process parameters of the leaves of three 
plant species (Ficus benghalensis, Syzigium cumini and Ocimum sanctum) were 
optimized by rotatable central composite design of chemometrics so as to get 
maximal yield of bio-actives. Phyto-blends of three species were prepared so as 
to achieve synergistic antidiabetic and antioxidant potentials and the ratios 
were optimized by chemometrics. Next, for in vitro screening of natural enzyme 
inhibitors the individual leaf extracts as well as composite blends were 
subjected to assay procedures to see their inhibitory potentials against the 
enzymes pathogenic in type 2 diabetes. The antioxidant potentials were also 
estimated by DPPH radical scavenging, ABTS, FRAP and Dot Blot assay.
RESULTS: Considering response surface methodology studies and from the solutions 
obtained using desirability function, it was found that hydro-ethanolic or 
methanolic solvent ratio of 52.46 ± 1.6 and at a temperature of 20.17 ± 0.6 gave 
an optimum yield of polyphenols with minimal chlorophyll leaching. The species 
also showed the presence of glycosides, alkaloids, and saponins. Composites in 
the ratios of 1:1:1 and 1:1:2 gave synergistic effects in terms of polyphenol 
yield and anti-oxidant potentials. All composites (1:1:1, 1:2:1, 2:1:1, 1:1:2) 
showed synergistic anti-oxidant actions. Inhibitory activities against the 
targeted enzymes expressed in terms of IC50 values have shown that 
hydro-ethanolic extracts in all cases whether individual species or composites 
in varying ratios gave higher IC50 values thus showing greater effectivity.
CONCLUSION: Current research provides the state-of-the-art of search of NEIs 
amongst three species by in-vitro assays which can be further utilized for 
bioactivity-guided isolations of such enzyme inhibitors. Further, it reports the 
optimized phyto-blend ratios so as to achieve synergistic anti-oxidative 
actions.
SUMMARY: The current research work focuses on the optimization of the extraction 
process parameters and the ratios of phyto-synergistic blends of the leaves of 
three common medicinal plants viz. banyan, jamun and tulsi by chemometrics. 
Qualitative and quantitative chemo profiling of the extracts were done by 
different phytochemical tests and UV spectrophotometric methods. Enzymes like 
alpha amylase, alpha glucosidase, aldose reductase, dipeptidyl peptidase 4, 
angiotensin converting enzymes are found to be pathogenic in type 2 diabetes. In 
vitro screening of natural enzyme inhibitors amongst individual extracts and 
composite blends were carried out by different assay procedures and the potency 
expressed in terms of IC50 values. Antioxidant potentials were estimated by DPPH 
radical scavenging, ABTS, FRAP and Dot Blot assay. Hydroalcoholic solvent 
(50:50) gave maximal yield of bio-actives with minimal chlorophyll leaching. 
Hydroethanolic extract of tulsi showed maximal antioxidant effect. Though all 
composites showed synergism, maximal effects were shown by the composite (1:1:2) 
in terms of polyphenol yield, antioxidant effect and inhibitory actions against 
the targeted enzymes. Abbreviations used: DPP4- dipeptidyl peptidase 4; AR- 
aldose reductase; ACE- angiotensin converting enzyme; PPAR-γ- peroxisome 
proliferator activated receptor-γ; NEIs- natural enzyme inhibitors; BE- binding 
energy; GLP-1- Glucagon like peptide -1; ROS- Reactive oxygen species; CAT- 
catalase; GSH-Px- glutathione per-oxidase; SOD- superoxide dismutase; pNPG- 
para-nitro phenyl-α-D-gluco-pyranoside solution; DPPH- 
1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl; RSM- Response surface methodology; CCD- central 
composite design; DMSO- dimethyl sulfoxide; HHL- hippuryl-L-histidyl-L-leucine; 
GPN-Tos- Gly-Pro p-nitroanilide toluenesulfonate salt; ESC- experimental 
scavenging capacity; TSC- theoretical scavenging capacity; FRAP- Ferric Reducing 
Assay Procedure; ABTS- 2, 2'- azinobis (3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6 - sulfonic 
acid.
