Molecular and Computational Studies on Apoptotic Pathway Regulator, Bcl-2 Gene 
from Breast Cancer Cell Line MCF-7.

Tiwari P(1), Khan MJ(2).

Author information:
(1)Department of Metabolic and Structural Biology, Central Institute of 
Medicinal and Aromatic Plants, (CSIR-CIMAP), Lucknow-226 015, India.
(2)Department of Biochemistry, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh-202 002, 
India.

Cancer is a dreadful disease constituting abnormal growth and proliferation of 
malignant cells in the body. Next to lung cancer, breast cancer is the most 
common form of cancer affecting women. The apoptotic pathway regulators, B cell 
lymphoma family of protein, play a key role in various malignancies defining 
cancer and their constitutive expression plays an integral role in breast cancer 
chemotherapy. The research work discusses the identification and molecular 
cloning of a B cell lymphoma like gene from human breast cancer cell line. The 
open reading frame of the gene consisted of 965 nucleotides, encoding a protein 
of 380 amino acids with a predicted molecular weight of 42.5 kilodalton. The 
predicted physiochemical properties of the gene were as follows: Isoelectric 
point - 9.49, molecular formula - C1893H3004N534O548S16, total number of 
negatively charged residues, (Aspartate+Glutamate) - 26, total number of 
positively charged residues, (Arginine+Lysine)-39, instability index-42.08 
(unstable protein) and grand average of hydropathicity is -0.202. Additionally, 
phobius prediction suggested non-cytoplasmic localization of the putative 
protein. The presence of secondary structure in the protein was determined by 
Memsat program. A 3 dimensional protein homology model was generated using 
threading based method of protein modeling for structural and functional 
annotation of the putative protein. Future prospects accounts for the 
biochemical characterization of the enzyme including in vitro assays on breast 
cancer cell line would establish the functional characteristics of the protein 
and its physiological mechanisms in breast cancer development and its 
therapeutic-target role in future.
