Iodine catalyzed simple and efficient synthesis of antiproliferative 
2-pyridones.

Buduma K(1), Chinde S(2), Arigari NK(1), Grover P(2), Srinivas KV(3), Kotesh 
Kumar J(4).

Author information:
(1)Natural Product Chemistry, CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic 
Plants-Research Centre, Boduppal, Hyderabad 500092, India.
(2)Toxicology Unit, Biology Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of Chemical 
Technology, Hyderabad 500007, India.
(3)Natural Product Chemistry, CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic 
Plants-Research Centre, Boduppal, Hyderabad 500092, India. Electronic address: 
kvnssrinivas@yahoo.co.in.
(4)Natural Product Chemistry, CSIR-Central Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic 
Plants-Research Centre, Boduppal, Hyderabad 500092, India. Electronic address: 
koteshkumarj@yahoo.com.

A simple and efficient method for the selective synthesis of 2-pyrdones from 
4H-pyrans using iodine as catalyst and ethanol as solvent was developed. The 
present method is equally effective for both aromatic and hetero aromatic ring 
containing 4H-pyrans. The compatibility with various functional groups, mild 
reaction conditions, high yields and application of inexpensive, readily and 
easily available iodine as catalyst and formation of 2-pyridones as major 
products are the advantages of the present procedure. In vitro antiproliferative 
activity of the final synthesized compounds was evaluated with four different 
human cancer cell lines (Lung adenocarcinoma-A549, Hepatocarcinoma-HepG2, Breast 
carcinoma-MCF-7 and Ovarian carcinoma-SKOV3) and normal human lung fibroblast 
cell line (MRC-5). Compounds 2b showed better inhibition against MCF-7, HepG2 
and A549 cell lines (IC50 8.00 ± 0.11, 11.93 ± 0.01 and 15.85 ± 0.04 μM, 
respectively) as compared with doxorubicin and also 2e showed moderate 
inhibition against MCF-7, HepG2 (IC50 9.32 ± 0.21 and 20.22 ± 0.01 μM, 
respectively, cell lines, respectively) as compared with doxorubicin. As many 
clinically used antiproliferative agents induce apoptosis in cancer cells hence, 
the 2-pyridone analogues were also tested for their ability to induce apoptosis 
in MCF-7 cells using the caspases-3 and -9 assays