Ocimum sanctum L (Holy Basil or Tulsi) and its phytochemicals in the prevention 
and treatment of cancer.

Baliga MS(1), Jimmy R, Thilakchand KR, Sunitha V, Bhat NR, Saldanha E, Rao S, 
Rao P, Arora R, Palatty PL.

Author information:
(1)Research and Development, Father Muller Medical College, Kankanady, 
Mangalore, Karnataka, India. msbaliga@gmail.com

Ocimum sanctum L. or Ocimum tenuiflorum L, commonly known as the Holy Basil in 
English or Tulsi in the various Indian languages, is a important medicinal plant 
in the various traditional and folk systems of medicine in Southeast Asia. 
Scientific studies have shown it to possess antiinflammatory, analgesic, 
antipyretic, antidiabetic, hepatoprotective, hypolipidemic, antistress, and 
immunomodulatory activities. Preclinical studies have also shown that Tulsi and 
some of its phytochemicals eugenol, rosmarinic acid, apigenin, myretenal, 
luteolin, β-sitosterol, and carnosic acid prevented chemical-induced skin, 
liver, oral, and lung cancers and to mediate these effects by increasing the 
antioxidant activity, altering the gene expressions, inducing apoptosis, and 
inhibiting angiogenesis and metastasis. The aqueous extract of Tulsi and its 
flavanoids, orintin, and vicenin are shown to protect mice against 
γ-radiation-induced sickness and mortality and to selectively protect the normal 
tissues against the tumoricidal effects of radiation. The other important 
phytochemicals like eugenol, rosmarinic acid, apigenin, and carnosic acid are 
also shown to prevent radiation-induced DNA damage. This review summarizes the 
results related to the chemopreventive and radioprotective properties of Tulsi 
and also emphasizes aspects that warrant future research to establish its 
activity and utility in cancer prevention and treatment.