Anticancer activity of plant leaves extract collected from a tribal region of 
India.

Kumar G(1), Gupta R(1), Sharan S(2), Roy P(2), Pandey DM(1).

Author information:
(1)1Department of Bio-Engineering, Birla Institute of Technology, Mesra, Ranchi 
India.
(2)2Department of Bio-Technology, Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee, 
India.

The goal of this research was to explore the preliminary anticancer properties 
of five plants namely Calotropis procera, Moringa oleifera, Millettia pinnata, 
Basela alba and Euphorbia neriifolia available in Jharkhand which is used for 
the medicinal purpose by local tribes. In the present study, plant leaves from 
five species were collected, dried and extracted with solvents of increasing 
polarity, followed by assessment of their cytotoxicity in A549 non-small-cell 
lung cancer cells. In the antimicrobial assay, the methanol extract of the M. 
pinnata leaves exhibited comparatively higher zone of inhibition of 
0.7 ± 0.20 cm against a Salmonella typhi culture than the other extracts. M. 
pinnata leaves extract also displayed the maximum percentage inhibition in the 
DPPH, 83.97 ± 0.01 FRAP, 193.14 ± 3.01 mM assays. Furthermore, the cytotoxicity 
of the chloroform (37.45 ± 1.04) and ethyl acetate extracts (34.20 ± 0.81) of M. 
pinnata against A549 cells was found relatively higher with respect to another 
extract. In contrast, a study with the L132 normal epithelial lung cell line 
revealed less toxicity from the chloroform extract (0.33 ± 0.19) compared to the 
ethyl acetate extract (6.65 ± 0.59). Based on these findings, phytochemical 
investigation on chloroform and ethyl acetate extract of M. pinnata was 
performed using UPLC-ESI-MS/MS analysis revealing the presence of β-sitosterol, 
lanceolatin B, karanjin, and stigmasterol. Congruently, a complete phytochemical 
and cytotoxic investigation of the M. pinnata extract constituents might infer 
the potency of this extract/s as anticancer, antioxidant and antimicrobial 
agents.
