Cytotoxic, Anti-inflammatory and Antioxidant Activities of Heliotropium indicum 
Extracts.

Chunthorng-Orn J, Dechayont B, Phuaklee P, Prajuabjinda O, Juckmeta T, Itharat 
A.

BACKGROUND: Heliotropium indicum Linn., or ‘Indian heliotrope’ is very common in 
India with a long history of traditional medicinal uses in many countries in the 
world. In Thailand, the plant has been traditionally use to cure various 
diseases such as fever, insect bites, stings, diarrhea, skin rashes, menstrual 
disorder and urticaria. In addition, the plant is commonly used by Thai folk 
doctors as a component in remedies for treatment of lung cancer.
OBJECTIVE: In the present study, we investigated cytotoxicity against two types 
of lung cancer cell lines (A549 and NCI-H226), anti-inflammatory effect and 
antioxidant activity of Heliotropium indicum extracts.
MATERIAL AND METHOD: The water and ethanolic extracts of Heliotropium indicum 
were tested. The cytotoxic activity against two types of human lung cancer cell 
lines (A549 and NCI-H226) was evaluated by sulforhodamine B (SRB) assay. The 
antiinflammatory effect was investigated on lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated 
RAW 264.7 macrophages. LPS-induced nitric oxide (NO) production was determined 
by Griess reagent. The antioxidant activity was performed by 1, 
1-diphenyl-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical scavenging method.
RESULTS: The ethanolic extract showed cytotoxic activity only against NCI-H226 
(IC50 = 51.90±2.35 μg/ml) whereas the water extract had no cytotoxic activity 
against both A549 and NCI-H226 (IC50 >100 μg/ml). For anti-inflammatory effect, 
the results revealed that the ethanolic extract exhibited the most potent 
inhibitory activity on nitric oxide production (IC50 = 24.17±2.12 μg/ml), 
followed by Indomethacin (positive control) with an IC50 value of 34.67±6.23 
μg/ml while water extract was apparently inactive (IC50 >100 μg/ml). For 
antioxidant activity, the ethanolic extract showed high antioxidant activity 
(EC50 = 28.91±4.26 μg/ml) but the water extract showed no antioxidant activity 
(EC50 >100 μg/ml).
CONCLUSION: These results can support using Heliotropium indicum Linn. for 
component in lung cancer remedy by Thai folk doctors. However, more studies are 
required.
