rigenin, a novel lead from Western Himalayan chemiome inhibits 
Fibronectin-Extra Domain A induced metastasis in Lung cancer cells.

Amin A(1)(2), Chikan NA(1)(3), Mokhdomi TA(1), Bukhari S(1)(4), Koul AM(1), Shah 
BA(1), Gharemirshamlu FR(5), Wafai AH(1), Qadri A(2), Qadri RA(1).

Author information:
(1)Department of Biotechnology, University of Kashmir, Srinagar (J and K), 
190006, India.
(2)Hybridoma Laboratory, National Institute of Immunology, New Delhi, 110067, 
India.
(3)Aaidah Life Sciences Pvt. Ltd., New Delhi, 110025, India.
(4)Molecular Reproduction, Development &Genetics Lab, Indian Institute of 
Science, Bangalore, 560 012, India.
(5)Department of Biology, Islamic Azad University, Kāzerūn, Iran.

Several lines of evidence indicate that Fibronectin Extra Domain A (EDA) 
promotes metastatic capacity of tumor cells by engaging cell surface α9β1 
integrins. This interaction mediated by the C-C loop of EDA activates 
pro-oncogenic signaling pathways leading to epithelial to mesenchymal transition 
(EMT) of tumor cells, thus signifying its importance in control of metastatic 
progression. In this context the present study was designed to explore the 
active compounds from selected ethno-medicinal plants of western Himalayan 
region for targeting EDA of Fibronectin in lung carcinoma cells. Structure based 
informatics for drug designing and screening was employed to generate a lead 
compound(s) feed that were conformationally and energetically viable. Out of 120 
compounds selected, Irigenin showed best binding-affinity with C-C loop of EDA. 
Irigenin specifically targeted α9β1 and α4β1 integrin binding sites on EDA 
comprising LEU46, PHE47, PRO48, GLU58, LEU59 and GLN60 in its C-C loop as 
evaluated by energy decomposition per residue of Irigenin-EDA complex. In-vitro 
cell motility assays complemented with EDA knock-in and knockdown assays 
distinctively demonstrated that Irigenin prevents metastatic capacity of lung 
cancer cells by selectively blocking EDA. The results presented thus project 
Irigenin as a lead compound to overcome Fibronectin EDA induced metastatic 
progression in lung carcinoma cells.