Cytotoxic Potential and Molecular Characterization of Fungal Endophytes from 
Selected High Value Medicinal Plants of the Kashmir Valley - India.

Dar RA(1), Qazi PH(1), Saba I(1), Rather SA(1), Wani ZA(2), Qazi AK(2), Shiekh 
AA(1), Manzoor A(1), Hamid A(2), Modae DM(2).

Author information:
(1)Biotechnology Division, CSIR - Indian Institute of Integrative Medicine, 
Sanatnagar - Srinagar, Kashmir, India.
(2)Cancer Pharmacology Division, CSIR - Indian Institute of Integrative 
Medicine, Jammu - Tawi, India.

The present study explores the fungal endophytes from selected high value 
medicinal plants to check their activities at in-vitro and in-vivo level. The 
in-vitro cytotoxicity of selected endophytes revealed potent growth inhibition 
against human cancer cell lines of leukemia (THP-1), lung (A549), prostate 
(PC-3), colon (Caco-2), neuroblastoma (IMR-32) and breast (MCF-7) at a 
concentration of 100 µg/ml. Among them the endophytic strains I. e., IIIM2, 
IIIM3, IIIM7 and IIIM8 showed most significant growth inhibition against colon 
(Caco-2), prostate (PC-3), lung (A549) and leukemia (THP-1) cancer cell lines. 
At the in-vivo level maximum (58.95%) tumor growth inhibition was documented 
with the extract of IIIM2 against Ehrlich Ascites Carcinoma mouse modal. All the 
potent fungal endophytic strains were characterized using ITS 4 and ITS 5 region 
sequencing and phylogenetic analysis was ascertained among them. This paper 
confirms the 2 elite endophytic fungal strains, IIIM2 and IIIM8, have the 
potential to act as a source of new anticancer compounds