Indian medicinal plants used in the Ayurvedic traditional system to 
treat diabetes are a valuable source of novel anti-diabetic agents. Pancreatic 
α-amylase inhibitors offer an effective strategy to lower the levels of 
post-prandial hyperglycemia via control of starch breakdown. In this study, 
seventeen Indian medicinal plants with known hypoglycemic properties were 
subjected to sequential solvent extraction and tested for α-amylase inhibition, 
in order to assess and evaluate their inhibitory potential on PPA (porcine 
pancreatic α-amylase). Preliminary phytochemical analysis of the lead extracts 
was performed in order to determine the probable constituents.
METHODS: Analysis of the 126 extracts, obtained from 17 plants (Aloe vera (L.) 
Burm.f., Adansonia digitata L., Allium sativum L., Casia fistula L., 
Catharanthus roseus (L.) G. Don., Cinnamomum verum Persl., Coccinia grandis (L.) 
Voigt., Linum usitatisumum L., Mangifera indica L., Morus alba L., Nerium 
oleander L., Ocimum tenuiflorum L., Piper nigrum L., Terminalia chebula Retz., 
Tinospora cordifolia (Willd.) Miers., Trigonella foenum-graceum L., Zingiber 
officinale Rosc.) for PPA inhibition was initially performed qualitatively by 
starch-iodine colour assay. The lead extracts were further quantified with 
respect to PPA inhibition using the chromogenic DNSA (3, 5-dinitrosalicylic 
acid) method. Phytochemical constituents of the extracts exhibiting≥ 50% 
inhibition were analysed qualitatively as well as by GC-MS (Gas 
chromatography-Mass spectrometry).
RESULTS: Of the 126 extracts obtained from 17 plants, 17 extracts exhibited PPA 
inhibitory potential to varying degrees (10%-60.5%) while 4 extracts showed low 
inhibition (< 10%). However, strong porcine pancreatic amylase inhibitory 
activity (> 50%) was obtained with 3 isopropanol extracts. All these 3 extracts 
exhibited concentration dependent inhibition with IC50 values, viz., seeds of 
Linum usitatisumum (540 μgml-1), leaves of Morus alba (1440 μgml-1) and Ocimum 
tenuiflorum (8.9 μgml-1). Acarbose as the standard inhibitor exhibited an IC50 
(half maximal inhibitory concentration)value of 10.2 μgml-1. Phytochemical 
analysis revealed the presence of alkaloids, tannins, cardiac glycosides, 
flavonoids, saponins and steroids with the major phytoconstituents being 
identified by GC-MS.
CONCLUSIONS: This study endorses the use of these plants for further studies to 
determine their potential for type 2 diabetes management. Results suggests that 
extracts of Linum usitatisumum, Morus alba and Ocimum tenuiflorum act 
effectively as PPA inhibitors leading to a reduction in starch hydrolysis and 
hence eventually to lowered glucose levels.
