Efficacy and safety of the dietary supplement DBCare® in patients with type 2 
diabetes mellitus and inadequate glycemic control.

Rotman-Pikielny P(1), Ness-Abramof R, Charach G, Roitman A, Zissin R, Levy Y.

Author information:
(1)a Department of Medicine E , Meir Medical Center , Kfar Saba , Israel.

AIMS: DBCare® (Ace Continental Exports Inc., London, UK) is a traditional Indian 
herbal food supplement marketed as an antidiabetes remedy. This study evaluated 
the efficacy and safety of DBCare in patients with inadequately controlled type 
2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) despite oral hypoglycemic treatment.
METHODS: A 12-week randomized double-blind placebo-controlled trial was 
conducted. Patients with T2DM on oral hypoglycemic agents with HbA1C > 7.0% were 
randomized to receive DBCare or placebo tablets.
RESULTS: Thirty-five patients (20 male/15 female; mean age 61.2 ± 7.6 years), 
with a mean baseline HbA1C of 7.9% ± 0.6%, received DBCare (N = 18) or placebo 
(N = 17). During the study period, HbA1C declined 0.4 ± 0.7% in the DBCare® 
group and 0.2% ± 0.8% in the placebo group (p = 0.806). No significant changes 
occurred in fasting plasma glucose, lipid profile, or homeostasis model 
assessment throughout the study or in body mass index, waist circumference, or 
blood pressure values. Hypoglycemic episodes (glucose < 70 mg/dL) were more 
frequent in the treatment group (7 vs 1, p = 0.043), necessitating a decrease in 
other hypoglycemic medications in 2 patients. DBCare was generally well 
tolerated, with mild side effects that were not different from those of the 
placebo group.
CONCLUSIONS: This preliminary study did not demonstrate that DBCare was 
efficacious in improving glycemic control in inadequately controlled patients 
with T2DM on oral hypoglycemics. A trend toward improved glycemic control was 
noted in the DBCare group, which correlates with more frequent hypoglycemic 
episodes. Further studies are needed to elucidate DBCare's hypoglycemic effect 
in patients with T2DM in general and in specific clinical settings, such as 
HbA1C ≥ 8%, short (≤10-year) duration of diabetes, or young age in particular.
