Anti-diabetic property of Tinospora cordifolia and its active compound is 
mediated through the expression of Glut-4 in L6 myotubes.

Sangeetha MK(1), Priya CD, Vasanthi HR.

Author information:
(1)Herbal and Indian Medicine Research Laboratory, Department of Biochemistry, 
Sri Ramachandra University, Chennai, India.

Tinospora cordifolia is a well reported plant possessing numerous medicinal 
values including anti-diabetic property. Aim of the present study is to study 
the mechanism of action of Tinospora cordifolia and its active compound in 
differentiated myocytes, L6 cells. Key marker of diabetes in cells is the 
insulin dependent glucose transporter-4 (Glut-4) which also responds to 
exogenous chemicals, and is over expressed up to 5- and 4-fold, by Tinospora 
cordifolia and palmatine, respectively. Next to Glut-4, the predominant protein 
influencing glucose metabolism is PPARα and γ whose expressions were also 
positively modulated. Further, the inhibitors of insulin pathway prevented 
glucose uptake mediated by Tinospora cordifolia and palmatine which shows that 
the activity is majorly mediated through insulin pathway.
