Withania somnifera (L.) Dunal (Solanaceae), known as Indian ginseng or 
ashwagandha, has been used in Indian Ayurveda for the treatment of a variety of 
disorders, such as diabetes and reproductive and nervous system disorders. It is 
particularly used as a general health tonic, analgesic, and sedative. As part of 
continuing projects to discover unique bioactive natural products from medicinal 
plants, phytochemical investigation of the roots of W. somnifera combined with a 
liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC/MS)-based analysis has led to the 
isolation of two novel phenylpropanoid esters, Withaninsams A (1) and B (2), as 
an inseparable mixture, along with three known phenolic compounds (3, 4, and 6) 
and a pyrazole alkaloid (5). The structures of the new compounds were elucidated 
using a combination of spectroscopic methods, including one-dimensional (1D) and 
two-dimensional (2D) nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) and high-resolution 
electrospray ionization mass spectroscopy (HR-ESIMS). Withaninsams A (1) and B 
(2) are phenylpropanoid esters that contain a side chain, 
4-methyl-1,4-pentanediol unit. To the best of our knowledge, the present study 
is the first to report on phenylpropanoid esters with 4-methyl-1,4-pentanediol 
unit. The anti-inflammatory activity of the isolated compounds (1-6) was 
evaluated by determining their inhibitory effects on nitric oxide (NO) 
production in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated RAW 264.7 macrophages, where 
compound 3 inhibited LPS-induced NO production (IC50 = 33.3 μM) and TNF-α 
production, a pro-inflammatory cytokine (IC50 = 40.9 μM). The anti-inflammatory 
mechanism through the inhibition of transcriptional iNOS protein expression was 
confirmed by western blotting experiments for the active compound 3, which 
showed decreased iNOS protein expression.