ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: Diabetes is a growing epidemic worldwide, 
especially among indigenous populations. Larix laricina was identified through 
an ethnobotanical survey as a traditional medicine used by Healers and Elders of 
the Cree of Eeyou Istchee of northern Quebec to treat symptoms of diabetes and 
subsequent in vitro screening confirmed its potential.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: We used a bioassay-guided fractionation approach to 
isolate the active principles responsible for the adipogenic activity of the 
organic extract (80% EtOH) of the bark of Larix laricina. Post-confluent 3T3-L1 
cells were differentiated in the presence or absence of the crude extract, 
fractions or isolates of Larix laricina for 7 days, then triglycerides content 
was measured using AdipoRed reagent.
RESULTS: We identified a new cycloartane triterpene (compound 1), which strongly 
enhanced adipogenesis in 3T3-L1 cells with an EC(50) of 7.7 μM. It is 
responsible for two thirds of the activity of the active fraction of Larix 
laricina. The structure of compound 1 was established on the basis of 
spectroscopic methods (IR, HREIMS, 1D and 2D NMR) as 
23-oxo-3α-hydroxycycloart-24-en-26-oic acid. We also identified several known 
compounds, including three labdane-type diterpenes (compounds 2-4), two 
tetrahydrofuran-type lignans (compounds 5-6), three stilbenes (compounds 7-9), 
and taxifolin (compound 10). Compound 2 (13-epitorulosol) also potentiated 
adipogenesis (EC(50) 8.2 μM) and this is the first report of a biological 
activity for this compound.
CONCLUSIONS: This is the first report of putative antidiabetic principles 
isolated from Larix laricina, therefore increasing the interest in medicinal 
plants from the Cree pharmacopeia.