Evaluation of Antidiabetic Potential of Sarcostemma brevistigma Wight & Arn. 
Using Alloxan-Induced Diabetic Murine Model.

Vijayalakshmi K(1), Selvaraj CI(2).

Author information:
(1)Research Scholar, Department of Biotechnology, School of Biosciences and 
Technology, Vellore Institute of Technology, Vellore, Tamil Nadu, 632 014, 
India.
(2)Research Scholar, Department of Biotechnology, School of Biosciences and 
Technology, Vellore Institute of Technology, Vellore, Tamil Nadu, 632 014, 
India. immanuelselvaraj@vit.ac.in.

A multimillion-dollar boom is achieved every year by the ethnopharmaceutical 
companies, creating awareness around the globe to use herbal medicines to stay 
and live a healthy life. Nearly, two-thirds of the plants were discovered for 
herbal remedies, and some plants are even endangered to get extinct from the 
globe for their repeated utility. Sarcostemma brevistigma is one among the 
undiscovered medicinal plants which belongs to the family Asclepiadaceae found 
distributed in Indian states of Bihar, Bengal, Konkan, Tamil Nadu, and Kerala. 
This study was intended to determine the antidiabetic property of plant extract 
of Sarcostemma brevistigma evidenced by biochemical parameters, antioxidant 
activity, with the histopathological analysis in diabetic induced mice. Animals 
that were orally treated with the S. brevistigma extract showed blood glucose 
lowering effect when compared to the alloxan-induced mice, i.e., from 
391.5 ± 6.3 to 193.6 ± 4.3 mg/dL. There is the significant increase in insulin 
level (P < 0.05) (27.97 ± 1.6 mIU/L) which is comparable to the metformin 
administered test group (30.35 ± 0.6 mIU/L). A significant difference (P < 0.05) 
of both ALT and AST levels were observed when compared to the other groups. A 
significant increase in antioxidant activity (reduced glutathione, 
malondialdehyde, superoxide dismutase) in plant extract administered group was 
observed when compared to the other treatment groups. Histopathological studies 
showed abnormalities in the liver, pancreas, kidney, lungs, heart, and spleen of 
alloxan-induced diabetic rats. The abnormalities were found to be normalized to 
a considerable extent after treatment with S. brevistigma extract. The results 
stood as evidence for S. brevistigma as an active antidiabetic herbal plant.