Erectogenic and Aphrodisiac Property of Moringa oleifera: Involvement of Soluble 
Epoxide Hydrolase Enzyme.

Goswami SK(1), Inamdar MN(1), Dethe SM(2), Gururaj GM(2), Jamwal R(2), Bhaskar 
A(2), Mundkinajeddu D(2), Agarwal A(2).

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacology, Al-Ameen College of Pharmacy, Bangalore, 560027, 
India.
(2)R&D Centre, Natural Remedies Pvt. Ltd., Plot No. 5B, Veerasandra Industrial 
Area, Bangalore, 560100, India.

Soluble epoxide hydrolase (sEH) inhibitors have been reported to improve penile 
erection; therefore, sEH could be useful for management of erectile dysfunction. 
Methanolic and aqueous extracts of 30 Indian medicinal plants were screened for 
their sEH inhibition potential. Fifteen extracts showed >50% inhibition when 
screened at 50 µg/mL in sEH inhibition assay. Methanolic extract of Moringa 
oleifera Lam. (Moringaceae) seeds (MEMO) was most potent with IC50 
1.7 ± 0.1 µg/mL and was selected for in vitro studies on isolated rat corpus 
cavernosum smooth muscle and in vivo sexual behaviour studies on healthy and 
diabetic rats. Rats were divided into five groups, each containing six animals 
and treated orally with either water, vehicle (1% Tween-20), MEMO (45 and 
90 mg/kg/day for 21 days), and standard drug, sildenafil (5 mg/kg/day for 
7 days). An equal number of female rats were used, and the effect of MEMO and 
sildenafil was compared with that of vehicle. MEMO significantly relaxed 
isolated rat corpus cavernosum smooth muscle at 0.1-100 µg/mL in vitro and 
significantly increased (p < 0.05) sexual activity, intracavernous pressure/mean 
arterial pressure in normal and diabetic rats. The increase in erectile function 
of rats by MEMO could be because of its sEH inhibitory activity. Copyright © 
2016 John Wiley & Sons, Ltd.
