Beneficial effects of an Andrographis paniculata extract and andrographolide on 
cognitive functions in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats.

Thakur AK(1), Rai G(2), Chatterjee SS(3), Kumar V(1).

Author information:
(1)a Neuropharmacology Research Laboratory, Department of Pharmaceutics , Indian 
Institute of Technology (Banaras Hindu University) , Varanasi , India ;
(2)b Department of Molecular and Human Genetics , Faculty of Science, Banaras 
Hindu University , Varanasi , India ;
(3)c Stettiner Straße 1 , Karlsruhe , Germany.

Context Andrographolide containing Andrographis paniculata (Burm. F.) Wall. Ex 
Nees (Acanthaceae) extracts is often used for treatments of diabetes and other 
inflammatory disorders commonly accompanying cognitive and other psychiatric 
disorders. Objective To compare the efficacies of a standardised A. paniculata 
extract (AP) and pure andrographolide on cognitive functions, oxidative stress 
and cholinergic function in diabetic rats. Materials and methods 
Streptozotocin-induced diabetic Charles Foster albino rats treated orally with a 
hydro-methanolic A. paniculata leaf extract (50, 100 and 200 mg/kg/day), or with 
pure andrographolide (15, 30 and 60 mg/kg/day) for 10 consecutive days, were 
subjected to Morris water maze test. After the test, acetylcholinesterase, 
superoxide dismutase (SOD), and catalase (CAT) activities and lipid peroxidation 
(LPO) in brain tissues were assessed. Results Acetylcholinesterase activity in 
pre-frontal cortex and hippocampus of diabetic rats was 2.1 and 2.6 times higher 
compared to nondiabetic rats. LPO was 1.6 times higher and decreased SOD (56.3%) 
and CAT (44.9%) activities in pre-frontal cortex of diabetic rats compared to 
nondiabetic rats. AP or andrographolide treatments dose dependently attenuated 
cognitive deficits, reduced acetylcholinesterase activity, oxidative stress, 
improved diabetic hyperglycemia and insulin deficiency. All observed effects of 
AP were quantitatively almost equal to those expected from its analytically 
quantified andrographolide content. Discussion and conclusion Reported 
observations are the very first ones suggesting beneficial effects of 
andrographolide against diabetes associated cognitive deficits, increased 
acetylcholinesterase activity and deteriorated antioxidative status. Efforts to 
exploit A. paniculata extracts enriched in andrographolide as preventive 
measures against such disorders can be warranted.