Anti-leptospiral activities of an endemic plant Glyptopetalum calocarpum (Kurz.) 
Prain used as a medicinal plant by Nicobarese of Andaman and Nicobar Islands.

Chander MP(1), Kumar KV, Shriram AN, Vijayachari P.

Author information:
(1)a Department of Medical Microbiology & Molecular Biology , Regional Medical 
Research Centre (Indian Council of Medical Research), WHO Collaborating Centre 
for Diagnosis, Reference, Research and Training in Leptospirosis , Post Bag No. 
13, Dollygunj, Port Blair 744101 , Andaman and Nicobar Islands , India.

Leaves of an endemic plant Glyptopetalum calocarpum are used by Nicobarese 
tribes of Andaman and Nicobar Islands, India, to prepare traditional medicine 
for treating fever. In the present investigation, pharmacologically active 
compounds were isolated from this plant and their antimicrobial efficacy was 
evaluated against the leptospiral strains. The anti-leptospiral activity of six 
plant-derived compounds was determined by both microdilution and macrodilution 
methods. Two out of six compounds, namely lupenone and stigmasterol, showed 
anti-leptospiral activity. The minimum inhibitory concentrations of the two 
compounds tested against pathogenic leptospiral strains belonging to 10 serovars 
were in the range of 100-200 μg/mL. The range of minimum bactericidal 
concentrations was 400-800 μg/mL. Compounds lupenone, stigmasterol, lupeol, 
β-amyrin and β-amyrin acetate had negligible or no haemolytic activity, 
exhibiting IC50 values of greater than 5 mg/mL. Further in vivo studies are 
needed to investigate the pharmacological and toxicological properties of G. 
calocarpum before it can be considered as a new anti-leptospiral agent.
