Carissa congesta Wight and Benincasa hispida (Thunb.) Cogn. as budding 
immunomodulatory agents.

Une HD, Doshi GM.

Carissa congesta and Benincasa hispida are well-known medicinally important 
plants associated with diabetes, inflammation, protozal infections and cancer. 
Here, we emphasized up on the immunomodulatory potential of these plants as the 
source of lupeol, P-sitosterol and ursolic acid. Petroleum ether extracts of C. 
congesta roots and B. hispida seeds were subjected to acute toxicity studies. 
They were screened for its immunomodulatory prospective in rats by 
Haemagglutination Antibody (HA) titre and Delayed-Type Hypersensitivity (DTH) 
response using Sheep Red Blood Cells (SRBCs of-0.5x10⁹) as antigens. Carbon 
Clearance test (Phagocytic Index) was estimated by Indian ink suspension. 
Complete Freund's Adjuvant (CFA) induced arthritis model interpretation was done 
by paw edema, kene joint erosion (transverse section), body weights, arthritic 
index and biochemical levels (RBC, WBC and Hb levels). Both the extracts were 
found to be therapeutically safe up to 5000 mg/kg. Dosage of 100 mg/kg was not 
satisfactory; and 500 and 250 mg/kg showed significant immunostimmulation (HA 
Titre) and immunosuppression (DTH response, 48 h). Benincasa hispida seed and 
Carissa congesta root extracts showed phagocytic Index of 0.0163±0.003, 
0.0145±0.003 and 0.0183±0.003, 0.0176±0.003 at 250 mg/kg and 500 mg/kg, 
respectively. CFA model revealed that the B. hispida seed and C. congesta root 
extracts decreased paw volume, knee joint erosion, increased body weights and 
biochemical parameters with an arthritic index of 1.31±0.12, 1.44±0.15 and 1. 
16±0.09, 1.36±0.13 at 250 mg/kg and 500 mg, respectively. The results were 
interpreted by One- way ANOVA followed by Dunnett test. Extracts showed 
relevance as promising immunostimulators as compared to control.
