Historical and modern medicinal plant uses--the example of the Ch'orti' Maya and 
Ladinos in Eastern Guatemala.

Kufer J(1), Förther H, Pöll E, Heinrich M.

Author information:
(1)Centre for Pharmacognosy and Phytotherapy, The School of Pharmacy, University 
of London, 29-39 Brunswick Square, London, WC1N 1AX, UK.

Local empirical knowledge about medicinal properties of plants is the basis for 
their use as home remedies. Particularly in developing countries such remedies 
still are an indispensable resource for everyday health care. They form the 
basis for numerous studies on drugs from natural sources. Like other indigenous 
groups across the world, the Ch'orti' Maya in Eastern Guatemala are currently 
experiencing a phase of dramatic cultural change, with their traditional 
knowledge about plants being in great danger of disappearing. During 17 months 
of fieldwork, medicinal plant uses were documented using a semi-quantitative 
approach and analysed using ethnopharmacological methods. The most important 
groups of illnesses treated with plants were gastrointestinal complaints and 
illnesses associated with pain and fever. Field data were compared with mostly 
unpublished historical data collected in the 1930s by the anthropologist Charles 
Wisdom. This comparison showed that medicinal plant uses that are more 
consistent over time are also shared by a larger number of people. A literature 
search on the most frequently mentioned medicinal plants showed that, even for 
widely used medicinal species, phytochemical and pharmacological data are 
insufficient for fully understanding their therapeutic profile. Whereas a few 
examples of potentially dangerous practices were encountered, the limited amount 
of information available mostly supports local medicinal plant usage.