The Indian Magical Herb 'Sanjeevni' (Selaginella bryopteris L.) - A Promising 
Anti-inflammatory Phytomedicine for the Treatment of Patients with Inflammatory 
Skin Diseases.

Paswan SK(1), Gautam A(2), Verma P(1), Rao CV(1), Sidhu OP(1), Singh AP(1), 
Srivastava S(2).

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacognosy & Ethnopharmacology, National Botanical Research 
Institute (CSIR), U.P., Lucknow, India.
(2)Amity Institute of Pharmacy, Amity University, Lucknow, India.

OBJECTIVES: Selaginella bryopteris L. (family: Selaginaceae), is often used in 
traditional Indian systems of medicine for the prevention and cure of several 
disorders and for the treatment of patient with spermatorrhoea, venereal 
disease, constipation, colitis, urinary tract infections, fever, epilepsy, 
leucorrhoea, beri-beri and cancer. It is also used as a strength tonic. This 
study aimed to evaluate the mechanisms underlying the anti-inflammatory effects 
of topically administered aqueous, polar and non-polar methanolic fractions (10 
mg/20 μL) of Selaginella bryopteris.
METHODS: An acute oral toxicity study of Selaginella bryopteris at doses from 
250 to 2,000 mg/kg body weight (bw) was performed. Aqueous, polar and non-polar 
methanolic extracts (10 mg/20 μL) applied topically for 5 days were evaluated 
for their anti-inflammatory effects against 12-tetra-O-decanoyl phorbol acetate 
(TPA)-induced inflammation by using the redness in the ear, the ear's weight 
(edema), oxidative stress parameters, such as lipid-peroxide (LPO) and nitric 
oxide (NO), and the pro-inflammatory cytokines involved in inflammation, such as 
tumour necrosis factor (TNF)-α, interleukin (IL)-1β and IL-6. Indomethacine (0.5 
mg/20 μL) was used for the positive control.
RESULTS: Selaginella bryopteris produced no mortalities when administered orally 
at doses from 250 to 2,000 mg/kg bw. Topical treatment with the non-polar 
methanolic fraction (10 mg/20 αL) significantly suppressed redness (2.4 ± 0.5) 
and edema (30.4 ± 1) and effectively reduced the LPO level (32.3 ± 3.3). The NO 
level was (8.07 ± 0.55), and the TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6 levels were decreased to 
69.6 ± 15.5, 7.7 ± 4.8 and 82.6 ± 5.9, respectively.
CONCLUSION: This study demonstrated for the first time the mechanisms underlying 
the anti-inflammatory effect of medicinal plants like Selaginella bryopteris and 
quantified the pharmacological interactions between them. The present study 
showed this herbal product to be a promising anti-inflammatory phytomedicine for 
the treatment of patients with inflammatory skin diseases.