Trapa bispinosa Roxb.: A Review on Nutritional and Pharmacological Aspects.

Adkar P(1), Dongare A(2), Ambavade S(2), Bhaskar VH(3).

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacology, JSPM's Jayawantrao Sawant College of Pharmacy and 
Research, Hadapsar, Pune,Maharashtra 411028, India ; Post Graduates Department 
of Pharmacology and Toxicology, JSPM's Jayawantrao Sawant College of Pharmacy 
and Research, Handewadi Road, Hadapsar, Pune, Maharashtra 411028, India.
(2)Department of Pharmacology, JSPM's Jayawantrao Sawant College of Pharmacy and 
Research, Hadapsar, Pune,Maharashtra 411028, India.
(3)Department of Pharmaceutical Medicinal Chemistry, Gahlot Institute of 
Pharmacy Plot No. 59, Sector No. 14, Koparkhairane, Navi Mumbai, Maharashtra 
400709, India.

Trapa bispinosa Roxb. which belongs to the family Trapaceae is a small herb well 
known for its medicinal properties and is widely used worldwide. Trapa bispinosa 
or Trapa natans is an important plant of Indian Ayurvedic system of medicine 
which is used in the problems of stomach, genitourinary system, liver, kidney, 
and spleen. It is bitter, astringent, stomachic, diuretic, febrifuge, and 
antiseptic. The whole plant is used in gonorrhea, menorrhagia, and other genital 
affections. It is useful in diarrhea, dysentery, ophthalmopathy, ulcers, and 
wounds. These are used in the validated conditions in pitta, burning sensation, 
dipsia, dyspepsia, hemorrhage, hemoptysis, diarrhea, dysentery, strangely, 
intermittent fever, leprosy, fatigue, inflammation, urethrorrhea, fractures, 
erysipelas, lumbago, pharyngitis, bronchitis and general debility, and 
suppressing stomach and heart burning. Maybe it is due to photochemical content 
of Trapa bispinosa having high quantity of minerals, ions, namely, Ca, K, Na, 
Zn, and vitamins; saponins, phenols, alkaloids, H-donation, flavonoids are 
reported in the plants. Nutritional and biochemical analyses of fruits of Trapa 
bispinosa in 100 g showed 22.30 and 71.55% carbohydrate, protein contents were 
4.40% and 10.80%, a percentage of moisture, fiber, ash, and fat contents were 
70.35 and 7.30, 2.05 and 6.35, 2.30 and 8.50, and 0.65 and 1.85, mineral 
contents of the seeds were 32 mg and 102.85 mg calcium, 1.4 and 3.8 mg Iron, and 
121 and 325 mg phosphorus in 100 g, and seeds of Trapa bispinosa produced 115.52 
and 354.85 Kcal of energy, in fresh and dry fruits, respectively. Chemical 
analysis of the fruit and fresh nuts having considerable water content citric 
acid and fresh fruit which substantiates its importance as dietary food also 
reported low crude lipid, and major mineral present with confirming good amount 
of minerals as an iron and manganese potassium were contained in the fruit. 
Crude fiber, total protein content of the water chestnut kernel, Trapa bispinosa 
are reported. In this paper, the recent reports on nutritional, phytochemical, 
and pharmacological aspects of Trapa bispinosa Roxb, as a medicinal and 
nutritional food, are reviewed.