Antimalarial and safety evaluation of Pluchea lanceolata (DC.) Oliv. & Hiern: 
in-vitro and in-vivo study.

Mohanty S(1), Srivastava P, Maurya AK, Cheema HS, Shanker K, Dhawan S, Darokar 
MP, Bawankule DU.

Author information:
(1)In-Vivo Testing Laboratory, Molecular Bioprospection Department, CSIR-Central 
Institute of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants, Lucknow 226015, Uttar Pradesh, 
India.

ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: Many of the effective therapeutic strategies 
have been derived from ethnopharmacologically used natural products. Pluchea 
lanceolata is an herb employed in Indian folk medicine for malaria like fever 
but it lacks proper pharmacological intervention.
AIM OF THE STUDY: To evaluate antimalarial and safety profile of Pluchea 
lanceolata: an in-vitro, in-vivo for its ethnopharmacological validation.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Methanol, butanol, ethyl acetate, chloroform, hexane 
extracts and its isolate, taraxasterol acetate (TxAc) were obtained from air 
dried aerial part of Pluchea lanceolata. These were tested in-vitro against 
chloroquine-sensitive strain of Plasmodium falciparum NF54 by measuring the 
parasite specific lactate dehydrogenase activity. The most potent hexane extract 
and TxAc were further validated for in-vivo antimalarial and safety evaluation. 
TxAc, a pentacyclic-triterpene isolated from the most active fraction was 
further evaluated with special emphasis on inflammatory mediators involved in 
malaria pathogenesis. Murine malaria was induced by intra-peritoneal injection 
of Plasmodium berghei infected red blood cells to the male Swiss inbred mice. 
Mice were orally treated following Peters 4-Day suppression test. In-vivo 
antimalarial efficacy was examined by evaluating the parasitaemia, percent 
survival, mean survival time, blood glucose, haemoglobin and pro-inflammatory 
mediators involved in malaria pathogenesis.
RESULTS: Hexane extract and TxAc showed promising antimalarial activity in-vitro 
and in-vivo condition. TxAc attributed in inhibition of the pro-inflammatory 
cytokines as well as afford to significant increase in the blood glucose and 
haemoglobin level when compared with vehicle treated infected mice. We have not 
observed the synergistic action of combinations of chloroquine and TxAc from our 
experimental results. In-vitro and in-vivo safety evaluation study revealed that 
hexane extract is non toxic at higher concentration.
CONCLUSION: Present study further validates the ancient Indian traditional 
knowledge and use of Pluchea lanceolata as an antimalarial agent. Study confirms 
the suitability of Pluchea lanceolata as a candidate for further studies to 
obtain a prototype for antimalarial medicine.
