Hemidesmus indicus induces apoptosis as well as differentiation in a human 
promyelocytic leukemic cell line.

Ferruzzi L(1), Turrini E, Burattini S, Falcieri E, Poli F, Mandrone M, Sacchetti 
G, Tacchini M, Guerrini A, Gotti R, Hrelia P, Cantelli-Forti G, Fimognari C.

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacy and BioTechnology, Alma Mater Studiorum-University of 
Bologna, Bologna, Italy.

ETHNOPHARMACOLOGICAL RELEVANCE: The decoction of the roots of Hemidesmus indicus 
is widely used in the Indian traditional medicine for the treatment of blood 
diseases, dyspepsia, loss of taste, dyspnea, cough, poison, menorrhagia, fever, 
and diarrhea. Poly-herbal preparations containing Hemidesmus are often used by 
traditional medical practitioners for the treatment of cancer. The aim of this 
study was to investigate the cytodifferentiative, cytostatic and cytotoxic 
potential of a decoction of Hemidesmus indicus's roots (0.31-3 mg/mL) on a human 
promyelocytic leukemia cell line (HL-60).
MATERIALS AND METHODS: The decoction of Hemidesmus indicus was characterized by 
HPLC to quantify its main phytomarkers. Induction of apoptosis, cell-cycle 
analysis, levels of specific membrane differentiation markers were evaluated by 
flow cytometry. The analysis of cell differentiation by nitroblue tetrazolium 
(NBT) reducing activity, adherence to the plastic substrate, α-napthyl acetate 
esterase activity and morphological analysis was performed through light 
microscopy (LM) and transmission electron microscopy (TEM).
RESULTS: Starting from the concentration of 0.31 mg/ml, Hemidesmus indicus 
induced cytotoxicity and altered cell-cycle progression, through a block in the 
G0/G1 phase. The decoction caused differentiation of HL-60 cells as shown by NBT 
reducing activity, adherence to the plastic substrate, α-naphtyl acetate 
esterase activity, and increasing expression of CD14 and CD15. The morphological 
analysis by LM and TEM clearly showed the presence of granulocytes and 
macrophages after Hemidesmus indicus treatment.
CONCLUSIONS: The cytodifferentiating, cytotoxic and cytostatic activities of 
Hemidesmus indicus offers a scientific basis for its use in traditional 
medicine. Its potent antileukemic activity provides a pre-clinical evidence for 
its traditional use in anticancer pharmacology. Further experiments are 
worthwhile to determine the in vivo anticancer potential of this plant decoction 
and its components.