Free radical scavenging, α-glucosidase inhibitory and anti-inflammatory 
constituents from Indian sedges, Cyperus scariosus R.Br and Cyperus rotundus L.

Kakarla L(1), Katragadda SB(2), Tiwari AK(3), Kotamraju KS(4), Madhusudana K(3), 
Kumar DA(3), Botlagunta M(1).

Author information:
(1)Biomedical Research Laboratory, Department of Biotechnology, K L E F 
University, Vaddeswaram, Guntur, Andhra Pradesh, India.
(2)Division of Natural Products Chemistry, CSIR-Indian Institute of Chemical 
Technology, Uppal Road, Hyderabad, India.
(3)Medicinal Chemistry and Pharmacology Division, CSIR-Indian Institute of 
Chemical Technology, Uppal Road, Hyderabad, India.
(4)Centre for Chemical Biology, CSIR-Indian Institute of Chemical Technology, 
Uppal Road, Hyderabad, India.

BACKGROUND: Cyperus scariosus R. Br and Cyperus rotundus L are widely used in 
ayurvedic preparation for the treatment of diabetes and other diseases. The 
early literature, so far, does not indicate the presence of any bioactive 
principle isolated from these plants.
OBJECTIVE: To identify free radical scavenging, anti-diabetic and anti- 
inflammatory principles from these two species.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: The bioassay guided fractionation and isolation of active 
constituents was done by chromatographic techniques. They also evaluated their 
anti-oxidant activity by DPPH and ABTS. The anti-diabetic activity was screened 
by α- glucosidase and α- amylase assays. Also, the further evaluation of in 
vitro anti-inflammatory activity using THP-1 monocytic cells and in vivo anti- 
inflammatory activity, was confirmed by carrageenan induced rat paw edema as 
model.
RESULTS: The activity guided isolation led to isolation of twelve compounds 
Which are: Stigmasterol[1], β- sitosterol[2], Lupeol[3], Gallic acid[4], 
Quercetin[5], β- amyrin[6], Oleanolic acid[7], β- amyrin acetate[8], 4- hydroxyl 
butyl cinnamate[9], 4- hydroxyl cinnamic acid[10], Caffeic acid,[11] and 
Kaempferol[12] respectively. Among the isolates, the compounds 4 and 5 displayed 
potent radical scavenging activity with an IC50 values of 0.43 and 0.067 ΅g/ml. 
The compounds 4, 5 and 10 showed significant anti-diabetic activities. while 
lupeol[3] showed potent IL-1 β activity inhibition in THP-1 monocytic cells and 
also displayed significant (p<0.0025) in vivo anti-inflammatory activity.
CONCLUSION: Inbrief, we isolated twelve compounds from both the species. 
Collectively, our results suggested that aromatic compounds showed good 
anti-oxidant and anti-diabetic activities.
SUMMARY: The study investigates the free radical scavenging, α-glucosidase 
inhibitory and anti-inflammatory effects of constituents isolated from Indian 
sedges viz. C. scariosus and C. rotundus. The results indicated that phenolic 
compounds displayed potent fee radical scavenging activty and alpha-glucosidase 
inhibition activity. While terpene constituent, Lupeol[3] showed good IL-1β 
activity inhibition in THP-1 monocytic cells and also displayed significant 
(p<0.0025) in vivo anti inflammatory activity in carrageenan induced rat paw 
edema. However, further studies are required to know the exact molecular 
mechanism. Abbreviations used: DPPH: 2,2- Diphenyl-1-1-picryl hydrazyl, ABTS: 
2,2-Azinobis-3-ethylbenzo thiazoline-6-sulfonic acid, THP-1: Human leukaemia 
monocytic cell line, IL-1β: Interleukin-1β, IC50-Inhibitory concentration 50%.