A molecular connection of Pterocarpus marsupium, Eugenia jambolana and Gymnema 
sylvestre with dipeptidyl peptidase-4 in the treatment of diabetes.

Kosaraju J(1), Dubala A, Chinni S, Khatwal RB, Satish Kumar MN, Basavan D.

Author information:
(1)Department of Pharmacognosy .

CONTEXT: Pterocarpus marsupium (PM) (Leguminosae), Eugenia jambolana (EJ) 
(Myrtaceae) and Gymnema sylvestre (GS) (Asclepiadaceae) are the most important 
medicinal plants in the Indian system of traditional medicine for the treatment 
of hyperglycemia.
OBJECTIVES: Dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (DPP-4) inhibitors are the emerging class of 
anti-diabetic agents. However, only few compounds are commercially available. 
Therefore, in the present study we tried to explore the naturally occurring PM, 
EJ and GS semi-standardized extracts for their potential DPP-4 inhibition in 
vitro and in vivo.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: DPP-4 inhibition was evaluated by in vitro inhibitory 
assay, and enzyme kinetics were calculated using one-phase exponential decay 
equation. Glucose load (2 g/kg) was administered to control and diabetic rats 
30 min following extract administration (100, 200 and 400 mg/kg) orally once, 
and blood samples were withdrawn at 0, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2 and 3 h to measure plasma 
active glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) levels.
RESULTS: PM and EJ inhibit DPP-4 potently with IC50 values of 273.73 ± 2.96 and 
278.94 ± 6.73 µg/mL, respectively, compared to GS (773.22 ± 9.21 µg/mL). PM, EJ 
and GS exhibit long duration of action with enzyme inhibitory half-lives of 
462.3, 317.2 and 153.8 min, respectively. Extracts significantly increase GLP-1 
levels compared to negative control groups and peak GLP-1 level was observed at 
2 h for PM and EJ, whereas for GS it was at 1.5 h
DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION: Taken together, results suggest the extracts may have 
potent DPP-4 inhibitory action, and their hypoglycemic action attributed through 
an increase in plasma active GLP-1 levels.
