Therapeutic potential of octyl gallate isolated from fruits of Terminalia 
bellerica in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats.

Latha RC(1), Daisy P.

Author information:
(1)Department of Biotechnology, Holy Cross College, Trichy 620002 Nadu, India. 
latha2611@gmail.com

CONTEXT: Medicinal plants are a potential source of antidiabetic drugs. 
Terminalia bellerica Roxb. (Combretaceae) is used in Indian traditional systems 
of medicine to treat diabetes mellitus.
OBJECTIVE: The aim of this study was to isolate and identify antihyperglycemic 
principle(s) from the fruits of T. bellerica and assess the bioactivity in 
streptozotocin (STZ)-induced diabetic rats.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Bioassay-guided fractionation was followed to isolate the 
active compound(s), structure was elucidated using (1)H and (13)C NMR, IR and 
mass spectrometry and administered intragastrically to diabetic Wistar rats at 
different doses (5, 10 and 20 mg/kg, body weight) for 28 d. Plasma glucose, 
insulin, C-peptide and other biochemical parameters were studied.
RESULTS: Octyl gallate (OG) isolated first time from the fruit rind of T. 
bellerica significantly (p < 0.05) reduced plasma glucose to near normal values 
(108.47 ± 6.9 mg/dl) after 14 d at the dose of 20 mg/kg. In addition, OG 
significantly increased plasma insulin, C-peptide, total protein, albumin, 
tissue glycogen, body weight and markedly decreased serum total cholesterol, 
triglyceride, LDL-cholesterol, urea, uric acid and creatinine in diabetic rats. 
Also OG restored the altered regulatory enzymes of carbohydrate metabolism.
DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION: OG might have augmented the secretion of insulin by 
the modulation of cAMP and intracellular calcium levels in the β cells of the 
pancreas. Our findings indicate that OG isolated first time from the fruit rind 
of T. bellerica has potential antidiabetic effect as it augments insulin 
secretion and normalizes the altered biochemical parameters in experimental 
diabetic rat models.