Herbal medicine has a long background equal to history of humankind. Several 
plants have been used as remedies in ancient Persian, Egyptian, Chinese and 
Indian civilizations. The plant Ocimum sanctum Linn. (Tulsi) is one of these 
medicinal plants with a wide variety of applications in traditional medicine. In 
modern era, it has been shown to be effective against diabetes mellitus, 
hypertension, cancers, bronchitis, and found to have anti-microbial properties. 
Several experimental studies have confirmed its anti-inflammatory properties and 
its role in modulation of both cellular and humeral immunity. Recently its 
efficacy against inflammatory response, hepatic injury and gastric ulcer has 
been elucidated in animal studies. In liver, essential oils and extracts of 
Ocimum sanctum could prevent oxidative stress by increasing glutathione 
peroxidae and catalase and were also effective in prevention of hepatic 
steatosis. In gastric epithelial tissue different derivatives of Ocimum sanctum 
had anti-ulcer and anti-secretory characteristics and could heal gastric 
ulceration. These beneficial properties of this medicinal plant can mainly 
originate from its major biochemically active constituents like eugenol, 
carvacrol, ursolic acid, β-caryophyllene and rosmarinic acid. Here in, we 
reviewed current literature about anti-inflammatory, gastric and 
hepatoprotective properties of Ocimum sanctum.