Traditional Indian and Australian medicinal plant extracts were 
investigated to determine their therapeutic potential to inhibit key enzymes in 
carbohydrate metabolism, which has relevance to the management of hyperglycemia 
and type 2 diabetes. The antioxidant activities were also assessed.
METHODS: The evaluation of enzyme inhibitory activity of seven Australian 
aboriginal medicinal plants and five Indian Ayurvedic plants was carried out 
against α-amylase and α-glucosidase. Antioxidant activity was determined by 
measuring (i) the scavenging effect of plant extracts against 2, 
2-diphenyl-1-picryl hydrazyl (DPPH) and 2, 
2'-azinobis-3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonate (ABTS) and (ii) ferric reducing 
power. Total phenolic and total flavonoid contents were also determined.
RESULTS: Of the twelve plant extracts evaluated, the highest inhibitory activity 
against both α-amylase and α-glucosidase enzymes was exerted by Santalum 
spicatum and Pterocarpus marsupium with IC50 values of 5.43 μg/ml and 0.9 μg/ml, 
respectively, and 5.16 μg/ml and 1.06 μg/ml, respectively. However, the extracts 
of Acacia ligulata (IC50 = 1.01 μg/ml), Beyeria leshnaultii (0.39 μg/ml), Mucuna 
pruriens (0.8 μg/ml) and Boerhaavia diffusa (1.72 μg/ml) exhibited considerable 
activity against α-glucosidase enzyme only. The free radical scavenging activity 
was found to be prominent in extracts of Acacia kempeana, Acacia ligulata 
followed by Euphorbia drummondii against both DPPH and ABTS. The reducing power 
was more pronounced in Euphorbia drummondii and Pterocarpus marsupium extracts. 
The phenolic and flavonoid contents ranged from 0.42 to 30.27 μg/mg equivalent 
of gallic acid and 0.51 to 32.94 μg/mg equivalent of quercetin, respectively, in 
all plant extracts. Pearson's correlation coefficient between total flavonoids 
and total phenolics was 0.796.
CONCLUSION: The results obtained in this study showed that most of the plant 
extracts have good potential for the management of hyperglycemia, diabetes and 
the related condition of oxidative stress.