The plant Diospyros melanoxylon (Roxb) belongs 
to the family Ebenaceae that is native to India and Sri-lanka. This is a 
medium-sized tree, reaching a height of 15 m and is well known for its beedi 
making leaves throughout the world. The purpose of the present study is to 
assess the effect of Diospyros melanoxylon leaves petroleum ether extract on 
blood glucose level, lipid level, insulin level, body weight, water and food 
intake in Streptozotocin (STZ) induced diabetic rats.
MATERIALS AND METHODS: Two different doses of extract AK001 (250 mg/kg) and 
AK002 (500 mg/kg) of Diospyros melanoxylon leaves were taken to evaluate 
different activities. The animals were divided into five groups namely normal 
control, diabetic control, reference group, AK001 and AK002 each containing six 
animals for in-vivo study. In-vitro study for antiadipogen activity was 
performed on 3T3-L1 cell line.
RESULTS: The extract showed dose dependent fall in Fasting Glucose Level (FSG) 
in experimental diabetic animals with significant reduction in food and water 
intake and increase in body weight. The extract exhibited hypocholesterolemic 
and hypotriglyceridemic effects while increased level of HDL in diabetes induced 
rats. In-vitro activity showed more than 75% viability of cells and significant 
inhibition in differentiated cells as compared to non-differentiate cells in 
3T3-L1 cell line. The extract exhibited the concentration-dependent inhibitory 
effect with an IC50 value of 689.22 μg/ml.
CONCLUSIONS: The extract exhibited significant results for antiadipogenic, 
antidiabetic and hypolipidemic activity both in-vivo and in-vitro and it may 
prove to be effective for the treatment of both types of diabetes, i.e. Insulin 
Dependent Diabetes Mellitus (IDDM) and Noninsulin Dependent Diabetes Mellitus 
(NIDDM).