Aqueous extract of some indigenous medicinal plants inhibits glycation at 
multiple stages and protects erythrocytes from oxidative damage-an in vitro 
study.

Tupe RS(1), Sankhe NM(1), Shaikh SA(1), Phatak DV(1), Parikh JU(1), Khaire 
AA(1), Kemse NG(1).

Author information:
(1)Biochemical Sciences Division, Rajiv Gandhi Institute of IT and 
Biotechnology, Bharati Vidyapeeth University, Pune, 411046 India.

Azadirachta indica, Emblica officinalis, Syzygium cumini and Terminalia 
bellirica are common in Indian system of traditional medicine for the prevention 
of diabetes and its complications. The aim of the present study was to 
comprehensively and comparatively investigate the antiglycation potential of 
these plant extracts at multiple stages and their possible protective effect 
against glycated albumin mediated toxicity to erythrocytes. Antiglycation 
activities of these plant extracts was measured by co-incubation of plant 
extract with bovine serum albumin-fructose glycation model. The multistage 
glycation markers- fructosamines (early stage), protein carbonyls (intermediate 
stage) and AGEs (late stage) are investigated along with measurement of thiols 
and β aggregation of albumin using amyloid-specific dyes-Congo red and Th T. 
Protection of erythrocytes from glycated albumin induced toxicity by these plant 
extracts was assessed by measuring erythrocytes hemolysis, lipid peroxidation, 
reduced glutathione and intracellular antioxidant capacity. Total phenolics, 
reducing power and antioxidant activities of the plant extracts were also 
measured. In vitro glycation assays showed that plant extracts exerted site 
specific inhibitory effects at multiple stages, with T. bellirica showing 
maximum attenuation. In erythrocytes, along with the retardation of glycated 
albumin induced hemolysis and lipid-peroxidation, T. bellirica considerably 
maintained cellular antioxidant potential. Significant positive correlations 
were observed between erythrocyte protection parameters with total phenolics. 
These plant extracts especially T. bellirica prevents glycation induced albumin 
modifications and subsequent toxicity to erythrocytes which might offer 
additional protection against diabetic vascular complications.
