Dry leaf extracts of Tinospora cordifolia (Willd.) Miers attenuate oxidative 
stress and inflammatory condition in human monocytic (THP-1) cells.

Reddi KK(1), Tetali SD(2).

Author information:
(1)Department of Plant Sciences, School of Life Sciences, University of 
Hyderabad, CUC, Prof. CR Rao Rd, Gachibowli, Hyderabad, Telangana State 500046, 
India; Department of Bioscience Research, College of Dentistry, University of 
Tennessee Health Science Center, Memphis, TN 38163, USA.
(2)Department of Plant Sciences, School of Life Sciences, University of 
Hyderabad, CUC, Prof. CR Rao Rd, Gachibowli, Hyderabad, Telangana State 500046, 
India. Electronic address: stetali@uohyd.ac.in.

BACKGROUND: Tinospora cordifolia (Willd.) Miers is known for its therapeutic 
value in Indian traditional medicine for treating diabetes, rheumatoid 
arthritis, jaundice and cardiac diseases. However, information regarding its 
protective role against inflammatory diseases at the molecular level is limited.
PURPOSE: The objective of the present work is to study the antioxidant and 
anti-inflammatory effect of alcoholic and water extracts of T. cordifolia 
(Willd.) Miers leaves in activated human monocytic THP-1 cells.
STUDY DESIGN/METHODS: Phytochemical analyses of the dry leaf extracts of T. 
cordifolia (Willd.) Miers prepared using the solvents alcohol (TCAE) or water 
(TCWE) are performed employing spectrophotometric methods for estimating total 
phenolic and flavonoid content, and the plant material was authenticated by 
detecting T. cordifolia (Willd.) Miers metabolite biomarkers using LC-MS/MS. 
Arachidonic acid (AA)- and lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-activated human monocytic 
(THP-1) cells were used as experimental models to investigate the antioxidant 
and anti-inflammatory activities of the plant extracts. Arachidonic acid 
(AA)-induced reactive oxygen species (ROS) in THP-1 cells were monitored by 
confocal microscopy/spectrofluorimetry and transcript of antioxidant enzyme 
catalase (CAT), by quantitative real time PCR. Lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced 
proinflammatory marker like TNF-α at transcription and protein levels in THP-1 
cells were measured by quantitative real-time PCR or ELISA respectively. 
Further, the effect of T. cordifolia (Willd.) Miers extracts on LPS-induced 
NF-κB translocation, and IκB and P-IκB protein levels, were studied by 
immunoblotting and confocal microscopy.
RESULTS: T. cordifolia (Willd.) Miers extracts exhibited significant amounts of 
total phenolic and flavonoid content, and LC-MS/MS analyses detected 
tinosponone, a TC-specific clerodane-derived diterpene. Both types of extracts 
attenuated AA-induced ROS generation via enhancing catalase enzyme activity in 
THP-1 cells. Real time PCR and ELISA experiments revealed that the elevated 
levels of LPS-induced TNF-α was remarkably attenuated in THP-1 cells pretreated 
with T. cordifolia (Willd.) Miers extracts. Western blot and confocal microscopy 
showed that the alcoholic extract's anti-inflammatory activity by attenuating 
NF-κB translocation into the nucleus in LPS-activated THP-1 cells via the 
inhibition of IκB degradation in the cytosol.
CONCLUSION: Our findings suggest that T. cordifolia (Willd.) Miers dry leaf 
extracts possess antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties via upregulation 
of antioxidant enzymes and attenuation of NF- κB nuclear translocation in 
activated human monocytic (THP-1) cells, therefore the present study supports 
our proposed molecular basis for the traditional use of T. cordifolia (Willd.) 
Miers for treating various inflammatory diseases.